<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The cobler of Caunterburie, or An inuectiue against Tarltons newes out of purgatorie A merrier iest then a clownes iigge, and fitter for gentlemens humors. Published with the cost of a dickar of cowe hides.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1590</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 153 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17918</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4579</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109603</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845250</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845250</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10138</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17918)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10138)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 188:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The cobler of Caunterburie, or An inuectiue against Tarltons newes out of purgatorie A merrier iest then a clownes iigge, and fitter for gentlemens humors. Published with the cost of a dickar of cowe hides.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 72 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Robinson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1590.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Tarltons newes out of purgatorie.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; K4, final leaf, torn, with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tarlton, Richard, d. 1588 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Tarlton's jests, and Newes out of purgatory --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10138:1"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The Cobler of <hi>Caunterburie,</hi> Or An Inuectiue againſt Tarltons Newes out of Purgatorie.</p>
            <p>A merrier Ieſt then a Clownes Iigge, and fitter for Gentlemens humors.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed with the cost of a dickar of Cowe hides.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Robert Robinson (McKerrow 244): "wreath enclosing armorial bearings—fretty with a martlet for difference"</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>AT LONDON, Printed by Robert Robinſon. 1590.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:10138:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10138:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The Coblers Epistle, to the Gentlemen Readers.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Hall a Hall (Gentlemen) roome for a Cobler, here comes the quainteſt ſquire in all Kent; The Cobler of <hi>Caunterburie,</hi> armde with his Aul, his Lingel, and his Laſt, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents himſelfe a Iudiciall Cenſor of other mens writinges: but mee thinkes, for my ſaucineſſe, I heare <hi>Apelles</hi> boy crying, <hi>Ne ſutor vltra crepidam.</hi> If I doe ſee his Maiſter mend the fault in the legge, Ile abide his frumpes, and when hee hath done, Ile ſay this had not been corrected but for the Cobler. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes not many a Tinker a tall Pratler? &amp; haue not men of my Trade waded ſo deepe in the ſecretes of Theology, that they haue ſought to correct <hi>Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficat?</hi> &amp; then by your leaue gentlemen, may not the Cobler of Kent who hath been the Patron of many good companions, and toſt ouer a paire of cards at
<pb facs="tcp:10138:3"/> Trumpe from morning till night, not to be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſo farre as to finde fault with <hi>Richard Tarltons news out of Purgatorie?</hi> Yes, &amp; if he that writ it wil not amend the latchet, Ile on with my night-cap and my ſpectacles, and make him ſhape the leg righter ere I haue done. I confeſſe tis a booke, and ſo is the Colliers Iade of Croyden a Horſe as well as the Courtiers Courſer: yet by my faith it hath a faire Title: but if <hi>Diogenes</hi> ſaw it, hee would cry out as hee did againſt <hi>Minda,</hi> ſtop your Citty that it runne not out of the gates; and inferre a like Inuectiue againſt the Booke, for that the Title conteines more then the whole Pamphlet: but yet in faith there is pretty ſtuffe in it, but vnworthy Dicke Tarltons humour: ſome where too low for Ieſtes, ſomewhere too hie for ſtile, If I diſtinguiſh like a Scholler, Gentlemen, thinke that I was borne when the Popes butterflies were abroad, and it may be, ſome Friar was my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the rather I geſſe it, for that nature hath wrought that vpon my crowne, that he had on his by Art: for before I was twenty, I had a bald pate. Well howſoeuer, I haue found fault, and therefore haue I attempted to amende it, not in the corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting of his worke, but in ſetting out one more pleaſant, and more full of delightfull tales for all mens humours: except thoſe which are ſo humo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous that they count nothing gracious, but that is too graue. What? a Dogge hath a day: <hi>Semel in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no ridet Apollo.</hi> Longer liues a merry man then a ſad; a Cobler hath leſſe cares then a King: and an
<pb facs="tcp:10138:3"/> hower paſt in honeſt myrth, is worth a tunne full of melancholy. Why were Tauernes inuented, but to ripen mens wits? And why were tales deuiſed, but to make men pleaſant? Tuſh when <hi>Redde ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem</hi> comes, I feare me there will be leſſe account to be giuen for honeſt recreation, then either for the enuious practiſes that ſolemne Saturniſtes rumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate: or for the ſundry ſchiſmes the melancholy michers doe publiſh. If my Principles bee falſe, let no man take exceptions, but paſſe it ouer with a ſmile: for tis but Coblers Philoſophie. But I di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe, and therefore to my booke, wherein are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the tales that were tolde in the Barge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Billinſgate and Graueſend: Imitating here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in old Father Chaucer, who with the like Methode ſet out his Caunterbury tales: but as there muſt be admitted no compare between a cup of Darby ale, and a diſh of durty water: So ſyr Ieffrey Chaucer is ſo hie aboue my reach, that I take <hi>Noli altum ſapere,</hi> for a warning, and onely looke at him with honour and reuerence. Here is a gallimaufre of all ſorts, the Gentlemen may finde <hi>Salem,</hi> to ſauour their eares with Ieſtes: and Clownes plaine dunſtable dogrell to make them laugh, while their leather buttons flie off. When the Farmer is ſet in his Chaire turning (in a winters euening) the crabbe in the fier, heere may hee heare how his ſonne can reade, and when he hath done laugh while his belly akes. The olde wiues that wedded themſelues to the profound hiſtories of Robin hood, Clim of the
<pb facs="tcp:10138:4"/> Clough, and worthy ſyr Iſenbras: may here learne a tale to tell amongſt their Goſſippes. Thus haue I ſought to feed all mens Fancies: which if I doe, was it not well done of a Cobler? If I offend, and they think there is in it neither rime, nor reaſon, why? a Cobler did it, and theres an end.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Farewell from my Shop whereſoeuer it be.</hi>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:10138:4"/>
            <head>¶Robin Goodfellowes Epiſtle.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Cobler become a Corrector? Ho, Ho, Ho: it was not ſo when <hi>Robin Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fellow</hi> was a Ruffler, and helpt the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie wenches to grinde their Mault: Then gentlemen, the Ploughſwaine medled with his Teame: the Gentlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with his Hound &amp; his Hawke: the Artificer with his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour: &amp; the Scholler with his booke: euery degree co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tented him within his limits. But now the world is growne to that paſſe, that Pierce Plow man will prie into lawe, naie into Diuinitie, and his duncerie must needs be doctrine: tuſh, what of higher powers? what of Vniuerſities? the text to put downe them, <hi>Babes &amp; Sucklings,</hi> and no more. This makes <hi>Robin Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fellow</hi> that was ſo merry a ſpirit of the Butterie, to leaue all and keepe himſelfe in Purgatorie, for Hoſpitalitie is ſo cleane run out of the Countrie, that he needs not now helpe the maids to grinde mault, for the drinke is ſo ſmall that it needes little corne: and if he ſhould helpe them, where he was woont to finde a meſſe of Creame for his labour, he ſhould ſcarſe get a diſh of floate Milke. Why? ſee you not how cranke the Cobler is, that will forſooth correct <hi>Dick Tarltons</hi> dooings, a man famous in his life for merrie conceits, and eſpecially a Booke of my publiſhing? well Gentlemen, if you ſuffer it, and <hi>Dick Tarlton</hi> pocket it vp without a reuenge, or a drie blowe at his breeche, <hi>Robin Goodfellow</hi> makes a vowe, to haunt him in his ſleepe, and after his olde merrie humour, ſo to playe the knaue with the Cobler, that hee ſhall repent hee medled ſo farre beyonde his latchet. But I will carrie my friends theſe
<pb facs="tcp:10138:5"/> newes to Purgatorie, where I know for anger he will almost breake his Taber, and will not rest till he haue reuenged: we will lay both our wits together, to put downe the paltring Cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, and heere I make a vowe, either to get the conquest, or els neuer to come in your ſightes: and to ſay as I was woont: What Himp and Hampe, heere will I neuer more grinde nor ſtampe.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours in choller,</hi> Robin <hi>Goodfellow.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:10138:5"/>
            <head>The Cobler of Caunterburie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Itting at the barge in Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingſgate expecting when the tide woulde ſerue for Graues ende, diuers paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers of all ſortes reſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thither to goe downe: at laſt it began to ebbe, and then they cried away; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I came to the ſtaires al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I was reſolued to goe downe in a tilt boate; yet ſéeing what a crue of madde companions went in the barge, and perceiuing by the winde there was no feare of raine, I ſtept into the barge and tooke vp my ſeate amongſt the thickeſt: with that the bargemen put from the ſtaiers, and hauing a ſtrong ebbe, becauſe there had much raine water fallen before, they went the more merrily downe, and ſcarſe had we gotten beyond ſaint Katherins, but that a perry of winde blewe ſome thing loude, that the watermen hoiſt vp ſailes and laide by their Oares from labour. Being thus vnder ſaile, going ſo ſnugly downe, it made vs all ſo merry, that wee fel to chat ſome of one thing and ſome of an other, al of myrth, many of knauery; that if <hi>Cato Cenſorius</hi> had béen there, he woulde either haue laughed at their knauiſh ieſts, or elſe at the confuſion of their prattles, which ſéemed like a very Chaos of ſundry conceites. As thus euery man was ſtriuing to paſſe away the time pleaſantly, a gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:10138:6"/> puld out of his ſléeue a little pamphlet and began to reade to himſelfe: amongſt the reſt my ſelfe was ſo bold, as to aſke him what book it was: marry quoth he, a fooliſh toy called <hi>Tarltons newes out of Purgatory,</hi> at this they fell to deſcanting of the booke, ſome commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it highly, and ſaide it was good inuention and fine tales: tuſh quoth an other moſt of them are ſtolne out of <hi>Boccace Decameron:</hi> for all that quoth the third, tis pretty and witty. As they were thus commending and diſcommending, there ſate by an auncient man that was a Cobler in <hi>Caunterbury:</hi> maſters quoth he, I haue read the booke, and tis indifferent, like a cup of bottle ale halfe one and halfe the other: but tis not merry inough for <hi>Tarltons</hi> vaine, nor ſtuffed with his fine conceites, therefore it ſhall paſſe for a booke and no more. No no what ſay you to old father <hi>Chaucer,</hi> how like you of his <hi>Caunterburie</hi> tales, are they not pleaſant to delight and witty to inſtruct, and full of conceited learning to ſhewe the excellencie of his wit? All men commended <hi>Chaucer</hi> as the father of Engliſh Poets, and ſaide, that he ſhot a ſhoote which many haue aimed at but neuer reacht to. Well quoth the Cobler, nowe that wee are going to <hi>Graues-end,</hi> and ſo I thinke moſt of vs to <hi>Caunterbury,</hi> let vs tell ſome tales to paſſe away the time till wee come off the water, and we will call them <hi>Caunterburie</hi> tales. To this motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the whole company willingly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented and onely they ſtood vpon this, who ſhould begin: If it be no offence quoth the Cobler, to other gentlemen that be here, I my ſelfe will be ringleader: to this they all agréed, and the Cobler began to ſettle himſelfe: yet before hee beginne, I will as néere as I can deſcribe you what manner of man he was.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The deſcription of the Cobler.</head>
               <l>HIs ſtature was large and tall,</l>
               <l>His lims well ſet withall.</l>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:10138:6"/>
               <l>Of a ſtrong bone and a broad cheſt,</l>
               <l>He was wide and wildſome in the breſt.</l>
               <l>His forehead hie and a bald pate,</l>
               <l>Well I wote he was a mate</l>
               <l>That had loued well a bonnie Laſſe,</l>
               <l>For the Lownes eies were as gray as glaſſe:</l>
               <l>And oft haue I heard my mother ſay,</l>
               <l>The wanton eie is ere moſt gray.</l>
               <l>He loued well a cup of ſtrong Ale,</l>
               <l>For his noſe was nothing pale:</l>
               <l>But his ſnout and all his face,</l>
               <l>Was as red as ruby or Topace.</l>
               <l>A voice ſhee had cleare and lowde,</l>
               <l>And well he gan ſing to a crowde.</l>
               <l>He was a ſtout ſturdie ſquire,</l>
               <l>And loued week daie good compire.</l>
               <l>Drinke he would with euerie man,</l>
               <l>In cup, cruſe glaſſe, or can:</l>
               <l>And what euerie daie he got,</l>
               <l>He hoorded vp in the Alepot:</l>
               <l>That all Caunterburie gan lere,</l>
               <l>To talke of this merrie Cobler<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
               <l>Therefore now marke me well,</l>
               <l>For thus his tale he gan to tell.</l>
               <div type="tale">
                  <head>The Coblers tale, Conteining the merrie Ieſtes paſſed betweene the Prior of Caunterburie, and a Smith of Saint Auſtins.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Prior of <hi>Caunterburie</hi> had a couent of Friar <hi>Auguſtines</hi> that were indued with great liuings, for the king and hee himſelfe had great reuenues, that he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued like a Potentate and was had in great eſtimation throughout all the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:10138:7"/> Citie: Liuing thus at eaſe pampred vp with delicates and idlenes the two Nurſes of Lechery, hee minded not ſo much his booke, but that paſſing one day through the ſtréetes, he glaunced his eies to ſee where he might finde ſome handſome trull that might be his Paramour: ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny he ſawe and many he liked, but at laſt comming by a Smiths forge, he ſpied a proper tall woman meanly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired after the pouerty of hir huſband; but of ſuch a beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull viſage and faire countenance, that ſhée pleaſed greatly the Priors eie, that he thought hir the faireſt in all <hi>Caunterburie:</hi> he returned home that way hee went out, becauſe he would haue an other looke at the Smiths wife, and as hee paſſed by he gaue hir a curteſie for his farewell. Well home he went to his Chamber, &amp; there he bethought him of his new loue, and caſt in his minde a thouſand waies how he might come to his purpoſe: At laſt hee ſent for the Smith to come looke on his horſe, who very haſtily hied him to the Priory, where the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or welcommed him and intertained him with great curteſie, kiſſing the Nurſe (as the olde prouerbe is) for the childs ſake, and making much of blacke <hi>Vulcan</hi> for faire <hi>Venus</hi> ſake: the poore Smith very carefully lookt to the horſe, and where ought was amiſſe amended it: The Prior and all his Couent gaue him great commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and thankes, and bidde him into breakefaſt, where he had good cheare and ſtore of ſtrong drink, which made the Smith paſſing pleaſant: as they ſate at breakefaſt the Prior tolde him, ſith they had made experience of his ſkill, and that he was cunning about horſes, he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to make him Farrier for the Priorie: At this the Smith was very glad: Nay more quoth the Prior be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou ſhall haue more gaines out of the Dorter, ſéeing thy wife is a good clenly woman, ſhée ſhal be Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe for mee, and the whole Couent. The Smith hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this, perceiued by the weathercocke which way the wind blew, ſhakt the head and began to ſmile: The Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:10138:7"/> demaunded of him why he laught: marry ſyr quoth he, ſéeing we are at meate, and mirth is good for digeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I will tell you a merry Ieſt. There was ſuch a poore man as my ſelfe that dwelt as I doe hard by a Priory, and he had brought vp in his houſe a litle Lambe, which growing to a ſhéepe woulde wander all abroade and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne home ſafe at night without any hurt; at laſt this litle ſhéepe beeing the poore mans treaſure, ſéeing the Priory gate open and the yarde full of graſſe went in and fedde there: The wanton Fryars that were idle, would oft ſport with the Lambe and play withall, and pulled off the wooll of the backe, that it had almoſt left nothing but the bare pelt: which the poore man eſpying kept vp his ſhéep and would not ſuffer it to go any more abroad: yet it had gotten ſuch a ſwéet ſauour in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ory yarde, that aſſoone as it brake looſe, it would thither; where the Prior and the Fryars ſpying it againe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented and eate it vp all: the good man came to aſke for his ſhéepe, and they laughing at him gaue him no other mendes but the hornes: So my Maiſters if my wife ſhould bee your Landreſſe, I warrant you, if I came to inquire for hir, I might haue ſuch fées as the poore man had for his loſſe: No, no I am well I thanke you, if my ſelfe may ſerue for a Farrier ſo it is, but my wife (of all men ſhall not haue to deale either with Priors or Fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars. At this they all laught, but the Prior not willing to giue ouer the chaſe, thus made this anſwere. Why Smith (quoth he) thou art a foole, thou maiſt haue a <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſo</hi> for that, for though ſhée waſh our clothes, yet ſhée ſhall neither fetch them nor bring them home, neither ſhall there euer a Fryar come at thy houſe, onely the Scull of the kitchin, and I hope thou feareſt not him. No quoth the Smith, they bee theſe bréechleſſe yeomen that I ſtand ſo much in doubt of: but vpon theſe condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions aforeſaide, that ſhée ſhall neither fetch them nor carry them home, ſhée ſhalbe your Landreſſe, vpon this
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:10138:8"/> they agréed, and the Smith went to his houſe and tolde his wife all. Shée that was a wily wench thought with hir ſelfe that whatſoeuer hir huſband fiſht for he would catch a frog; and that dealt hee neuer ſo warily, yet ſhée woulde make him one of the head men of the pariſh as well as his neighbours. Shée coniecturing thus with hir ſelfe, the next morning came the Scull early (by that the Smith was vp and at his worke) with foule clothes, God ſpéede ſyr quoth he. I haue brought your wife the Priors linnen; ah welcome good fellow quoth he, goe thy waies vp the Chamber to my wife, ſhée is aboue, and I thinke a bed: the Scul trotted vp the ſtaires &amp; ſaluted the woman: Miſtres quoth he, the Prior hath ſent you his cloathes &amp; praies you they may bee done on wedneſday next: they ſhall be done quoth ſhée with all ſpéede: and quoth the Scull, his worſhip wild me in ſecrete to giue you a Ring for a token, and to deſire you to thinke that he loues you as heartily as any woman in the worlde: the poore wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſéeing a gold Ring, and hauing neuer had any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in hir life, helde hir ſelfe a proude woman, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought her what good gifts ſhée ſhould daily haue if ſhée had ſuch a louer as the Prior: wherefore ſhée returned him this anſwere by the Scull, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhée had euer thought well of him, but hir huſband was a iealous foole &amp; watcht hir narrowly whereſoeuer ſhée went, but as far as ſhée might, ſhée was his at command. Home went the Scul, and the Prior was riſen by that hee returned, and aſkt him what newes: what newes quoth the Scull, marry thus ſyr, aſſoone as I came to the doore I founde the Smith hard at his worke, and I ſaluted him by the time of the day, and aſked him where his wife was, ſaying, I had brought the Priors linnen. Goe vp the ſtaires, good fellow quoth he, for I thinke my wife is in bed, and Syr there indéede I found hir, and truely Syr if you will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue me, me thought ſhée lay to louely in hir bed to lie with a Smith, ſo ſyr I gaue hir your token and tolde hir
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:10138:8"/> what you bad me: and ſhe made anſwere that your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip was the man whom ſhée had euer thought well of, but hir huſband was a iealous foole, yet as farre as ſhée could ſhée was at his commaund. This ſatiſfied the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors expectation, and on wedneſday morning when the Scull ſhoulde goe for his cleane linnen, the Prior com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded with him and gaue him a braſe of Angels to kéepe his counſaile: ſaying, <hi>Tom</hi> (for ſo was the Sculs name) thou knoweſt al fleſh is fraile, and we are men as well as others, though our profeſſion be more holy, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Tom</hi> ſo it is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I haue loued the Smiths wife a long time, &amp; now may I haue opportunity to fill my deſires, I wil this morning take thy clothes on, &amp; beſméere my face and with the baſket hie for the cleane clothes, onely I care for nothing if thou kéepe my counſaile. Feare not that ſyr, quoth the Scull, but I will bee ſo ſecrete as you can deſire: with that the Prior was briefe for becauſe he longd to be there, and on with the Sculs rags, and taking his baſket on his necke, hied him very orderly to the Smiths houſe by that time day did appeare, where he found him hard at worke: God morrow ſyr quoth the Prior, I am come for the linnen, goe vp the ſtaires fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low quoth the Smith, thou commeſt very early, my wife is yet in bed. Vp trudgd the Prior, and there he founde his Paramour in a ſwéete ſléepe, the Prior ſtept to hir and kiſt hir, and with that ſhée wakte, and ſeeing the Scull, why how now ſyr ſauce, quoth ſhée, can you not ſpeake before you come vp? my huſband is a wiſe man to ſend ſuch companions vp into the Chamber where I am in bedde, twere no matter and the match were equall, to make him weare the horne for it. Oh bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent good loue quoth the Prior, for knowe I am not <hi>Tom</hi> the Scull, but the Prior himſelfe that ſent thée the Ring, who for thy ſake is come thus diſguiſed: with that he diſcouered him ſelfe, and ſhée perceiued it was he and bluſht: hee kiſt hir, and ſo coniured hir, that while the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:10138:9"/> poore Smith was knocking at the Smithy he had dudeb him knight of the forked order, and for feare of ſuſpition putting his linnen in the baſket away he went, bidding the Smith farewell. Thus the Prior and the Smiths wife contented and inioying their hearts deſire, the poore Smith loued hir not a whit the worſe, neither did he ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect any thing, for the blind eates many a flie, and much water runs by the mill that the miller wottes not on: ſo plaid it with this Smith, for twiſe a wéeke came the Prior in his Sculs apparrell to his lemmon, thus it continued till on one morning the Prior was not well, ſo that he could not goe; but <hi>Tom</hi> Scul after his woon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted manner went to carry foorth the linnen, and as hee went by the way, he began to thinke with himſelfe what a faire woman the Smiths wife was, and how faine he would be partaker with his Maiſter, hammering this in his head, on hee went to the Smiths houſe: Nowe Smith quoth he good morrow, is thy wife vp. No quoth the Smith but ſhée is awake, goe vp and carry your lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen a Gods name: Vp came the Scull, and ruſhing in at the Chamber doore threw downe his baſket, and ſéeing the Chamber darke that he could not be diſcouered, ſlipt to bed and entred Commens with the Prior, and with that got him away without ſaying one worde: The Smiths wife maruailed at this, and ſuppoſing that hee had heard ſome ruffling, and for feare of hir huſband had gone away ſo haſtily. Well within two daies after came the Prior againe, and after his accuſtomed maner went vp with his baſket and ſaluted hir after the old faſhion: I pray you tell me maiſter Prior quoth ſhée, what meant you yeſterday morning that you came ſo quiet, and ſlipt away with ſuch ſilence after you got out of bed: by this the Prior perceiued that the Scull had cut a ſhiue on his loaf, and ſo thought to diſſemble the matter. Faith ſwéet heart quoth he, I heard a noiſe, and thought it had béene thy huſband that had come vp ſo I coniectured quoth
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:10138:9"/> the Smiths wife, and therefore after you were gone, ſéeing you were freighted with your owne ſhadowe I laught hartily: thus as long as they durſt they chatted, but at laſt the Prior vp with his baſket and away. When he came home, in a great chafe hee ſent for the Scull and made inquiry of the matter, the poore fellow afraide of ſore threatninges, confeſſed the matter and craude pardon: but the Prior forgetting his patience fell vpon poore <hi>Tom</hi> the Scull and beate him ſo ſore, that he had almoſt kild him: afterwards ſwearing him on a booke, if euer after hee went with any clothes, hee ſhould go no further then the Chamber doore. The Scul agréed to this, and confirmd it with a ſolemne oath: but the remembrance of his ſore blowes, bred him a minde to reuenge: wherevpon reſoluing to doe any miſchiefe to the Prior that he might, one day he went very order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to his Smith and carried him to the Alehouſe, and there after a long proteſtation of ſilence, reuealed the whole matter vnto him, how the Prior euery day came in his apparrell to his wife, and ſo made him weare the horns whiles he was buſie about his hammers: at this the Smith fetcht a great ſigh; alas quoth he, and am I a Cuckolde? why not you quoth the Scul, as well as your betters? Indéede quoth the Smith, that is all the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort that I haue, that my betters haue had as hard hap: for the Abbot of ſaint <hi>Peters</hi> that is an holy man, had but one Lemman, and yet ſhée was not content with twenty morſels: and I am a poore Smith &amp; a lay man, no maruaile then if my fortune be as forked as the reſt: but by the holy Roode of Rocheſter quoth he, I will bee ſo reuengd on the Prior, that after I haue taken him, he ſhall hate Lechery the worſe while he liues. I but quoth the Scul, take héede thou plaguſt not me in ſtéede of the Prior. To auoid therefore all inſuing danger, if I come to morrow thou ſhalt knowe mee by this token, I will aſke thée whether thou haſt drunke this morning or no:
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:10138:10"/> if thou heareſt no ſuch watchword, then knowe it is the Prior. So bee it quoth the Smith, and vpon this they drunke their drinke and departed. The next morning the Smith was early at his worke, and the Prior that longde to be with his Lemmon was aſſoone awake, and vp hee got, and on with the Sculs apparrell, and to the Smiths houſe, and after his accuſtomed maner bad him good morrow and vp the ſtaires. The Smith perceiuing it was the Prior, becauſe hee wanted his watchworde, hied vp preſently after him, and tooke the Prior in bed with his wife: why how nowe Scull quoth hee? will no worſe meate go downe with you then my wife? Before you and I part, I will learne you howe you make <hi>Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can</hi> of mee without you were more like <hi>Mars</hi> then you be. Whereupon his man and he (two luſty knaues) ſtept to him and puld him out of bed, and thruſt him in a great ſacke wherein he was woont to put chaffe: when he had done, carried him into the ſtréet, and laid him downe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his doore, and then made his wife take a flaile in hir hand, and threſh as hard as ſhée coulde: but becauſe hee perceiued hir ſtroakes were laide on with fauour, him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſtoode behind hir with a great Carters whip, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery time ſhée fainted in hir blowes hee lent hir a laſh, that he fetcht the bloud through hir petticoate: the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that came by maruailed at this Antick, and aſkt the Smith, what he was a doing? killing of fleas quoth the Smith, that I found this morning in my bedde, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe my wife is ſo idle and will not ſtrike home, I ſtand with my whip to whet hir on. Neighbours there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore giue good eare, and marke the end, and ſée when my wife hath beaten them enough what foul fleas they be, and by my example learne whenſoeuer you take ſuch great fleas in your wiues bedde, to put them to the like puniſhment. The people flocked together to ſee this ſport, and although the Prior was almoſt bruiſed to death (though for fauouring of him the Smiths wife
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:10138:10"/> bore many a laſh) yet he durſt not cry for feare of further diſcredit, but lay ſtill and ſuffered all with patience. At laſt a multitude of people flocking together, it chaunced that vppon ſerious buſineſſe the Abbot of ſaint <hi>Peters</hi> came by, who ſéeing ſuch a throng, ſent one of his men to knowe what the matter meant. Oh may it pleaſe your Lordſhip quoth the Smith, ſuch a ſight as you neuer ſaw! wherfore for Chriſts ſake I aſke it, that you would take ſo much paines as to come ouer the way and ſée: the Abbot ſtept ouer the Channell, and when hee came and ſaw the Smiths wife with hir flaile, and him with his whip, he woondred, &amp; the Smith told him as the reſt, that it was a flea that he tooke in his wiues bed: all this while lay the Prior with a heauy heart, for feare the Smith ſhoulde ſhake him out of the ſacke: wiſhing to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide twiſe as much torment, ſo hee might eſcape vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne. As the Abbot about this matter ſtoode queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with the Smith, the Scull that miſt the Prior that paſt his howre, thought the Smith had plaid ſome mad prancke with him, went and put on the Priors appar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, and his Coole ouer his heade that hee might not be knowen, and went downe to the Smiths houſe ward, where ſéeing a concourſe of people hee haſted him thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. At laſt the Smith ſpied him and cryed, Oh my Lord Abbot yonder comes the Prior of ſaint <hi>Auſtins,</hi> it was one of his fleas. Wel knew the Smith it was <hi>Tom</hi> Scull, but his wife ſuppoſing it to be the Prior, and that he in the ſacke was the Scul that had deceiued hir, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpight for reuenge laid on ſuch blows, that ſhée néeded no whipping to mend hir ſtrokes. When the Prior came, &amp; after moſt humble maner had ſaluted the Abbot, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to knowe the cauſe of this ſtrange ſight: marry quoth the ſmith, Maiſter Prior, I may thanke you for this, for a flea of your Priory hath leapt from the Dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to my wiues bed, and finding it there this morning, I put it in a ſacke and cauſed my wife to threſh it, and for
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:10138:11"/> that both you &amp; Maſter Abbot, &amp; al my neighbors ſhall ſée what parlous fleas oft happen into womens beds; I will ſhake him out before you all, &amp; with that he vnbound the ſacke, and he threwe out the Prior, who beeing in the ſculs apparrell, was ſo beſmiered and ſo bloudy, that he could not be knowen: Looke here Maiſter Prior quoth the ſmith, here is the ſcull of your Priory. Oh notable knaue knaue quoth <hi>Tom</hi> ſcull, ſo to diſcredit our houſe, what thinke you of this my Lorde Abbot? is this a ſufficient puniſhment or no, conſidering by this fault he ſhal giue occaſion of ſlaunder to the whole Priory? He is quoth the Abbot, within the iuriſdiction of your cenſure, and therefore deale with him as you liſt. Marry quoth the ſcul then thus: becauſe it is an open fault, it ſhal haue a more open puniſhment; for if it be ſmothered vp thus, they wil ſay that I am a fauourer of ſinne: with that he cald to certaine of his couent, for moſt of the Monkes of the Priory were come thither, howe ſay you brethren quoth he, is it not beſt that he ſtand all this forenoone on the Pillory, and haue a paper written on his heade con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the whole matter of his offence? and the ſmiths wife ſhall ſtand vnder him with hir flaile, and the ſmith with his whip: and ſo quoth the ſmith ſhall all <hi>Caunter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burie</hi> laugh at me that come into the market place to proue my ſelfe a Cuckolde. No goodman ſcull quoth he, it ſhal not be ſo, and with that he puld of his Coole and ſaid, Maſters and neighbours, ſée here is the ſcul of the houſe, and this beaten in the ſacke is the Prior himſelfe that came to my wife in the ſculs apparrell: at this all the people clapt their hands, laught &amp; made good game, to ſée howe ſimply the Prior ſtood and in what a maieſtie the ſcull was in the Priors abiliments. At this ſight the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot abaſht, and the Friars were aſhamde: but the ſcull nothing amaſed, began afore all the people to ſay thus: my Maiſters quoth hee, I was once a ſcholler, though I am now a ſcul, and then I learned this old ſaying in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:10138:11"/> 
                     <hi>Caute, ſi non Caſte:</hi> Liue charily, if not chaſtly: Bee not ſo forwarde in your follies that you diſcouer your faults to the whole worlde, and eſpecially was this ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to men of the Churche, for in that they knowe much, and doe dehort others from vice, the people looke their liues and their learning ſhoulde agrée: but when they offend ſo groſſly as Maiſter Prior through his ill example, to bring a whole houſe in ſlaunder, then are they worthy of double puniſhment: for we know Friars are men, and I warrant you, there is a great many in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d haue done as much to others as he hath done to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſmiths wife, &amp; yet haue ſcapt without diſcredit: I hope my Lord Abbot, if you enter into your owne conſcience, you can verifie as much, and therefore ſéeing hee was ſo careleſſe of his credit, let him for euer after (to auoid per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall infamie of the houſe) be baniſht out of the Prio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. To this they agréed, and the people that heard this collation ſaid, <hi>Tom</hi> ſcull was worthy to be Prior: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Abbot and the Fryars conſenting, and ſéeing he had good learning, turned away the old Prior and made <hi>Tom</hi> ſcull Prior in his roome: thus was the Prior pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht for his Lechery, the Smith reuengde for his Cuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koldry, and the ſcull for his blowes ſtumbled on a good promotion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>At this merry tale of the Cobler, all they in the barge laught and ſaide the ſmith was well reuenged: I but quoth the Cobler, ſo he was made a Cuckold, and with a heauy head was the poore ſmith faine to goe to his ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, beeing euer after noted for a Cuckolde through all <hi>Caunterburie.</hi> There ſate a ſmith hard by, who grieued at this, that hee ſhoulde deſcant ſo vpon his occupation, and the rather perchaunce hee tooke pepper in the noſe, becauſe he was of the ſame fraternity, if not with a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or, yet with ſome other good fellowe, and therefore in a ſnuffe he beganne thus to reply: Why Cobler quoth hee,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:10138:12"/> doſt thou hold the ſmith in ſuch deriſion becauſe hee was a Cuckold? I tell thée Cobler, Kinges haue wore hornes: and tis a fault that Fortune excepteth from none: yea, the olde writers haue had it in ſuch queſtions, that they haue ſet downe diuers degrées of Cuckoldes. I marry quoth the gentleman, <hi>Tarlton</hi> in his Purgatory hath di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided them into thrée ſorts. Tuſh quoth the ſmith, <hi>Tarl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> was a foole or hee that writ the booke, for to tell you truth there bee eight degrées, and that I can prooue: At this there was a great laughter, and euery man deſired him to tell what they were: that I will quoth the ſmith, they be theſe.</p>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="list">
                     <body>
                        <head>The eight orders of Cuckolds.</head>
                        <p>Cuckold.
<list>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>1 Machomite.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>2 Hereticke.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>3 Lunaticke.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>4 Innocent.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>5 Incontinent.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>6 By conſent.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>7 By Act of Parliament.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>8 <hi>Quem facit Eccleſia.</hi>
                                 </hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>And becauſe quoth the Smith they may ſéeme darke and obſcure to you, I will briefly make an expoſition of them to you, and that is in this manner.</p>
                  <div type="exposition">
                     <head>The expoſition of the eight degrees of Cuckolds.</head>
                     <p n="1">1 Cuckolde <hi>Machomite</hi> is an auncient Cuckold, who hath béene married ſome thirty or forty yeares, and euer ſince his firſt marriage hath continued content in that eſtate, being ſo knowen and notified amongſt his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, therefore being the oldeſt, he is the formoſt.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 Cuckold <hi>Hereticke,</hi> is he that hauing a faire wife
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:10138:12"/> and honeſt, is ſo blinded with Iealouſie and ſuſpition, as he thinkes hir to be as diſhoneſt as the beſt, but indéed is none, and therefore conſumes himſelfe in an hereſie.</p>
                     <p n="3">3 Cuckold <hi>Lunaticke,</hi> is he that being a Cuckold con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiues ſuch inward griefe, that he ſuffers his paſſions to take no reſt, but as a man diſtrackt from his ſenſes doth all things ſo out of order, as though he were Lunaticke: and therefore hath this title for his humours frenzie.</p>
                     <p n="4">4 Cuckold <hi>Innocent,</hi> is hee that being ſimple of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſuſpecteth nothing, but what ſoeuer hee heares of his wife, beléeueth no more then hee ſées, knowing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and therefore ſuſpecting nothing.</p>
                     <p n="5">5 Cuckold <hi>Incontinent,</hi> is hee that marries himſelfe to a wife of a light diſpoſition, who maketh him a Cuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kold the very firſt day of his marriage.</p>
                     <p n="6">6 Cuckold by conſent, is he that of al other Cuckolds is moſt infamous, who is not onely headed as brauely as the reſt, and hath one of light conuerſation, but fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtereth his wife vp in hir follies, and is content to kéepe the doore to his wiues laſciuious wantonneſſe, conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to more then the ſtrumpet is aſhamde to performe.</p>
                     <p n="7">7 Cuckold by <hi>Act of Parliament,</hi> is ſuch a one that when he takes his wife faulty is not content ſecretly to puniſh the offence, but goes to lawe with the man for recompence: the Queſt giuing him perhaps for dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage ſome i.d.ob. whereby it is regiſtred in the Court by his owne proofe that he is a Cuckold, and therefore is he called Cuckold by <hi>Act of Parliament.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="8">8 Cuckolde <hi>Quem facit Eccleſia,</hi> is hee whome the Church maketh a Cuckold, and that is this, when a yong
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:10138:13"/> man marrieth a maide or a wife, whome hee ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth to be a maide, and yet hath plaid falſe before, and perhaps hath had a childe or two: In marrying him to ſuch a one he is Cuckolde in the Church, and therefore called Cuckold <hi>Quem facit Eccleſia.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thus quoth the Smith, haue you heard my degrées, and their expoſition, and becauſe I will bee quit with the Cobler for the tale of the Smith, giue me leaue a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and you ſhall heare a merry Ieſt, but becauſe I will let you knowe what manner of man hee was, before his tale, heare his deſcription.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The deſcription of the Smith.</head>
               <l>THis Smith I weene was a quaint ſire,</l>
               <l>As merry as byrd on brier.</l>
               <l>Iocund and gleeſome at euery ſith,</l>
               <l>His countenance aie buxſome and blith,</l>
               <l>His face was coaly and full blacke,</l>
               <l>Hued like vnto a Colliers ſacke,</l>
               <l>Or as if it had beene ſoild with mier,</l>
               <l>Full of wrinckles was his cheekes with the fier.</l>
               <l>Well he could ſweat and ſwinke,</l>
               <l>And one that aie loued good drinke,</l>
               <l>For hard by his Forge alwaies ſtoode</l>
               <l>A ſtond of ale nappy and good:</l>
               <l>Which made the colour of his noſe,</l>
               <l>Like to the fier when it glowes.</l>
               <l>His head great, his browes broad,</l>
               <l>Able to beare a great load:</l>
               <l>As no man might hold it ſcorne</l>
               <l>On his head to graft a horne.</l>
               <l>His coates were fit for the weather,</l>
               <l>His pilch made of ſwines leather:</l>
               <l>So was his breech, and before</l>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:10138:13"/>
               <l>A duſtie apron he wore:</l>
               <l>Wherein not to faile,</l>
               <l>Was many a horſe ſhoo naile,</l>
               <l>And for to fit him euerie tide,</l>
               <l>Hung an hammer by his ſide,</l>
               <l>Thus attyred the Smith gan ſay,</l>
               <l>What befell on a ſummers day.</l>
               <div type="tale">
                  <head>The Smiths tale, Conteining a pleaſant ieſt of a iealous Cobler, and how for all his ſuſpition, he was cunningly made Cuckold.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N <hi>Rumney</hi> Marſhe by the ſea coaſt, there dwelled a Cobler, a merry fellow, and of his middle age: who was woont on working-dayes to chaunt it out at his worke, and on holy-dayes to beſturre his ſtumpes in the Churchyard ſo merrily after a crowd, that he was wel-beloued of all the countrey wenches, and noted for the flower of good fellowſhip throughout all the pariſh. This Cobler kéeping ſhop for himſelfe, had in houſe with him an old mother of his, who being as it were his ſeruant, deſirous to liue more at eaſe, wiſht him to take a wife: the Cobler was loth to be perſwaded to marriage, and the reaſon was, for that he feared to be a Cuckold: yet at laſt he caſt his eye on a countrie laſſe, that was a blythe and bonny wench, and the chéefe of all the maides of old <hi>Rumney:</hi> to hir was this iolly Cobler a ſuter, and after a little wooing (as women muſt be got with prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and promiſes) the Cobler caught her, and married they muſt be in all haſte, which doone, they liued plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly together, as fools do preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly after their wedding: but after the honnie moone was paſt, ſhe like a good huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife fell to her worke, to ſpin and carde, and ſuch other déedes of huſwiferie as belonged to the profite of her houſe: the Cobler loued hir well, and ſhee wanted
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:10138:14"/> nothing that might ſatiſfie hir humor, onelye ſhe was charged by hir huſband, not to goe abroad a goſſipping with hir neighbours: inſomuch that either on work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-dayes or on holy-dayes, when all the wiues in <hi>Romney</hi> went to bee merry, ſhee was faine as a poore priſoner to kéepe home: which although ſhe paſſed ouer with ſylence and patience, ſo yet ſéeing his iealouſie was without cauſe, ſhe vowed with hir ſelfe if euer a fréend and oportunitie ſerued to hir minde, to make him weare a horne an inch longer then all his neighbours: but he kept hir ſhort from that, for euery day when ſhee was at home, ſhe ſat by him in the ſhop, where he ſoong like an Nightingale, hauing his eye neuer of his wiues face; or if ſhe ſat within, hir mother in law an olde iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous woman bore hir company; if ſhe went to fetch wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, hir mother was at hir elbow; whatſoeuer ſhe did, or whether ſo euer ſhe went, to be bréefe, hir huſband, or hir mother was at one end, which gréeued the yoong wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. So ſuſpitious and iealous was this Cobler, that all <hi>Romney</hi> talked of his folly: and to vexe him as they paſſed by, would ſay to him; ah neighbour good morrow, now that you haue gotten a faire wife, we hope to haue you one of the brotherhood, and that the Cuckow in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prill may ſit and ſing in your houſe as well as with your poore neighbours. I feare not that quoth the Cobler, let hir doo hir woorſt, I will giue hir leaue, meaning that he kept ſuch narrow watch ouer hir, as he could neuer be deceiued, and therefore euery day his wife ſitting by him when he was yerking of his ſhooes, and ſhe at hir whéele, then he would chat out this ſong.</p>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="song">
                     <body>
                        <head>The Coblers ſong.</head>
                        <lg>
                           <l>WHen as the Nobilitie pull downe their towers,</l>
                           <l>Their manſion houſes and ſtately bowers:</l>
                           <l>And with ſtone and timber make hoſpitals free,</l>
                           <l>Then the Cobler of Romney ſhall a Cuckold be.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <pb n="19" facs="tcp:10138:14"/>
                           <l>When Gentlemen leaue of their Peacockly ſutes,</l>
                           <l>And that all their workes are charities fruites:</l>
                           <l>Tendring the poore which needy they ſee,</l>
                           <l>Then the Cobler, &amp;c.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>When Vſurers run vp and downe with their gould,</l>
                           <l>And giue it to them from whome it was pould:</l>
                           <l>And Colliers ſackes ouer great you do ſee,</l>
                           <l>Then the Cobler, &amp;c.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>When Weſtminſter hall is quite without benches,</l>
                           <l>And Southwarke Banckeſide hath no prettie wenches,</l>
                           <l>When in Smithfield on Fridaies no iades you can ſee,</l>
                           <l>Then the Cobler, &amp;c.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>When Maides hate mariage, and loue to liue chaſt,</l>
                           <l>Virgins forſooth till foureſcore be paſt:</l>
                           <l>And loue not that yoongmen their beauties ſhould ſee,</l>
                           <l>Then the Cobler, &amp;c.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>When wiues are not wilfull, but needs will obay,</l>
                           <l>When ſilent and ſpeechleſſe they ſit a whole day:</l>
                           <l>When Goſſips do meete, and no words there wilbe,</l>
                           <l>Then the Cobler, &amp;c.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>When womens toongs doo ceaſe for to wagge,</l>
                           <l>And ſhoomakers giue not their maiſters the bagge:</l>
                           <l>When Cuckolds and keepers want hornes for their fee,</l>
                           <l>Then the Cobler, &amp;c.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>When tapſters and alewiues from Berwick to Douer,</l>
                           <l>Fill thirding deal pots till the drinke run ouer,</l>
                           <l>When the quart is ſo full that no froth you may ſee,</l>
                           <l>Then the Cobler, &amp;c.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>When Smithes forſweare to drinke of ſtrong Ale,</l>
                           <pb n="20" facs="tcp:10138:15"/>
                           <l>And liue without liquor whiles their noſes be pale:</l>
                           <l>When in Vintners wine no mixture you ſee,</l>
                           <l>Then the Cobler, &amp;c.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>When Dutchmen hate butter, and the Spaniards pride,</l>
                           <l>When Cardnars do want a trull by their ſide:</l>
                           <l>When the Pope like Peter humble you ſee,</l>
                           <l>Then the Cobler, &amp;c.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>Euery day did the Cobler vſe to ſing this ſong, and there dwelled next vnto him a Smith that was a tall and a yoong luſty fellow, proper of perſonage, of a comely viſage, curteous, gentle, and debonaire, ſuch a one as this Coblers wife could haue wiſhed to hir Paramour, if time and oportunity would haue fauoured hir fancie: and the Smith ſéeing what a ſmocker wench the Cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers wife was, and what a iealous foole ſhée had to hir huſband, ſorrowed at the good fortune of the Cobler, that hee had ſo faire a wife, and wiſhed that hee coulde finde meanes to haue ſuch a one to his friend: vpon this, being next neighbours, and their houſes ioining together, the Smith woulde oftentimes when his leiſure ſerued him come to the Coblers ſhop and talke with him; where be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéen the Smith &amp; the Coblers wife paſſed ſuch glaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that he perceiued there was no want, but place and oportunity to fulfill their deſires. One day amongſt the reſt, Fortune ſo fauored this yoong couple, that the Cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler went foorth to buy Leather, and left his mother and his wife in the ſhop: the old woman not hauing ſlept the laſt night was heauy and fell a ſléepe, and the young wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſate ſinging at hir worke. The Smith perceiuing this, laid by his hammers and went to the ſtal, where he ſaluted his neighbour, and ſhe returned him the like cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie.</p>
                  <p>At laſt ſéeing the olde beldame was ſure, he began to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:10138:15"/> reueale vnto hir how long hee had loued hir, and how hee was ſorry that ſhée was combred with ſuch a one as for his iealouſie, aboue all other men deſerued to be made a Cuckolde: ſundry ſpéeches paſt betwéene the Smith and the Coblers wife, till at laſt ſhée roſe, and gaue him hir ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, that ſhée loued him better then any man in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, and woulde if any occaſion woulde ſerue, euer ſtriue to content him. Then ſwéete heart quoth he, doe mee but this fauour, faine to morrow ſome occaſion to go to your Mothers, and come on the further ſide of the way faſt by ſuch a doore, and then let mee alone for oportunity to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfie both our deſires: To this ſhee agréed, and the Smith went to his Shoppe: preſently the olde wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man wakte, the Cobler came home, and all was well.</p>
                  <p>At night when they were in bed, taking him about the necke ſhée kiſt him, and tolde him that certaine of hir friendes met to morrowe at hir Mothers, and that ſhée woulde faine goe and ſée them, I pray you good huſband quoth ſhée, let your mother and I goe thither, I will not part out of hir ſight, neither will we make any long tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riance: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> huſband for ſhame could not deny this requeſt, but granted it: whereupon the next morning ſhée got hir vp, and on with hir holyday apparrell, and made hir as ſine as ſine might bee: the Cobler ſéeing his wife ſo trickt vp in hir cleane Linnen, beganne to bee iealous, and calde his Mother aſide, and charged hir by that loue ſhée bare him, not to let his wife part out of hir company till ſhée came home againe, which ſhée promiſed with an oath: ſo away they went, &amp; the Cobler he ſet him downe and began to ſing.</p>
                  <p>The Smith that all this day was not idle, had compounded with an olde woman by whoſe houſe ſhée muſt paſſe, to fauour them with houſe roome, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed vnto hir all the matter: whoſe wife it was, and howe hee woulde haue his purpoſe brought
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:10138:16"/> to paſſe: by my troth ſonne quoth ſhe, I haue hard much talke of that iealous Cobler, and I would do my inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to make the Aſſe were a horne: vpon this they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued, &amp; ſhe likt well of his policie, &amp; ſaid loue had many ſhiftes, at laſt the Smith ſpied his miſtreſſe all in her brauerie, comming with her mother in law: the old wife was readye, as ſhee paſt by the doore, threw a great bowle full of bloudy water right vpon hir head, that all her cloathes, and cleane lynnen was marred, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo berayde that ſhee could goe no further: alas miſtreſſe quoth the old woman, I crie you mercie, what haue I done? full ſore it was againſt my will: but for Gods ſake come into the houſe, and ſhift you with cleane linnen: if you haue none at home, I will lend you of the beſt that I haue, goe in daughter, quoth hir olde mother in law, it is a chance, and againſt an ill turne ſometime no man may be: ile goe home as faſt as I can, and goe fetch you cleane linnen, the whiles drie your gowne, and make all things els ready. I pray you do good mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (quoth ſhe) and next way goes hir mother in lawe: and aſſoone as ſhe was out of doores, the old woman led hir into an inwarde Parlour where the Smith was, and there theſe two louers by this policie made the iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Cobler were the horne.</p>
                  <p>Whiles thus they were ſolacing themſelues, the old wife ſhe came ſtumbling home, and for haſte had like to breake hir necke ouer the threſhould, her fall made the Cobler ſtart, and when he ſaw it was his mother, and that he miſt his wife, he was halfe mad, and aſkt his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haſtily where ſhe was: the old woman ſhort win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded was almoſt out of breath, and for a good ſpace ſat puffing and blowing to fetch winde; at laſt ſhe cryed out: alas deare ſonne, ſuch a chaunce as neuer was hard of: as we went through old <hi>Romney,</hi> hard by the church, a woman threw out a bowle of bloudie water right vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your wiues head, which hath ſo berayed hir linnen
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:10138:16"/> and hir gowne, that ſhe could go no further, and ſo I as faſt as I could came running home for clean clothes: oh for the paſſion of God mother quoth he, hie to hir cheſt, and get hir cloathes ready, for it may be a fetch to make the poore Cobler a Cuckhold; a horne mother is ſoone grafted: with that the old woman got all in a readines, and away ran the Cobler &amp; his mother together. Well the two louers out at a little hole kept good watch and warde, that anon they ſpied where the Cobler and his mother came trudging: in went his wife, and ſat hir downe by the fier, where the Cobler found her onely ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with the old woman in hir petticoate, drying hir gowne, aſſoone as ſhe ſaw him ſhe wept: and he although he gréeued at the miſchance, yet for that hee ſpied hir in no companie, he was ſatiſfied, and wiſht hir to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, &amp; ſent for a pot of béere or two to make hir drinke: and after he had ſéene all well, and his wife in hir cleane apparell, ſetting them a little on the way; home he went againe to his ſhop, and his wife went to hir mothers, where an houre or two ſhe paſt away the time in chat, and then returned home with hir mother in law. Thus the Cobler was not ſuſpitious of his wiues being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, but tooke hir miſfortune for a chaunce, and the Smith euery day according to his woonted cuſtome, would come and chat with his neighbour the Cobler, and ſometimes found opportunitie to talke with the wife, but neuer out of the ſhop: on a day the Cobler be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from home, and the old woman within péecing of hir hoſe, the Smith came to the ſhop, and finding hir alone, began to lay a plot, how to make hir huſband a Cuckold, while he held the doore: ſhe promiſt if he would deuiſe it, ſhe would put it in practiſe, and ſo agréed they concluded betwéene themſelues, and they brought it cunningly to paſſe, thus.</p>
                  <p>It chaunced within a fortnight after, that as the Cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler and his wife lay in bed, ſhe fell on a great laughter,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:10138:17"/> hir huſband demaunding the cauſe, ſhe made him this anſwer. I will tell you huſband a ſtrange thing, ſo it is, that this other day when you went to buie Lether, my mother and I ſat in the ſhop, and ſhe fel faſt a ſléepe, your neighbour the Smith, he, as his cuſtome is, came to the window, and ſéeing my mother a ſléepe, began to court me with faire words and large promiſes, and told me, that if I would find the meanes that when you were out, I would let him lie with me, he would giue me for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſhillings. I ſhakt him off as well as I could, but he would haue no nay at all, but threw foure Angels into my lap: wherevpon I tooke the golde, for me thought they were foure fayre péeces, and promiſed him that to morrow you went foorth, and my mother to, and then he ſhould finde me alone in the chamber. Vpon this hee went away, and left me the gold, and therfore if it pleaſe you, to morrow I thinke good you ſhould faine your ſelfe to go abroad, and my mother to, and then hide you in a chamber bard by, and aſſoone as he is come in, you may ſtand at the doore and heare all our talke: when you heare me conſent, then break in, and take the Cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, and ſwindge him well, and I warrant you huſband there will diuerſe commodities riſe of it: for not onely we ſhall haue this gold, and get more for amends, but euer after be rid of ſuch a knaue.</p>
                  <p>This motion pleaſed the Cobler well, &amp; the rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Smith profeſt to be his great fréend, and yet would ſéeke to doo him ſuch diſgrace: vpon this conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion they reſolued, and ſo fel a ſléepe. The next day in the afternoone, the Cobler fained himſelfe to go out, and his mother with him, and after comming home at a backe doore went vp into the next chamber, &amp; hid themſelues, by and by according vnto promiſe came the Smith, and went roundly vp to the chamber, where hee found the Coblers wife: wherefore ſtraight ſhutting the doore with a boult in the inſide, he fell to ſet vp plumes on the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:10138:17"/> Coblers head-péece, the Cobler he very eaſtlie got to the doore with a great pollax in his hand, and began to li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten: with that he hard the ſmith offer faire to his wife: nay (quoth ſhe) I haue kept promiſe with you, for I one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly promiſed to let you vp into my Chamber: tuſh quoth he, this is but a cauill? and many words paſt betwéene them: the Cobler and his mother ſtanding at the doore, with her naye and his yea, till the Cobler had a new browantler growne out of his old hornes; and then ſhee anſwered him, ſéeing nothing would content him, hee ſhould haue his pleaſure: with that the Cobler was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to ruſh in, but that his mother ſtaid him, and bid him harke further: and dooſt thou meane good faith, quoth the Smith? I wherefore elſe (quoth the Coblers wife) came we into this place? why then (quoth the Smith) heare what I will ſay to thée: Dooſt thou thinke, though we be héere in ſecret, that our faults will not be ſéene open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? that though thy huſband knowes not of, and that it is kept cloſe from the world, that there is not one aboue that ſées all, &amp; wil reuenge it? yes vilde ſtrumpet as thou art, &amp; for this cauſe came I to trie thée: thou haſt an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt man to thy huſband, who loues thée more déerly the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> himſelfe, who works hard, to ſuffer thée y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou ſhalt not want, and wilt thou in his abſence wrong him? thinke if euer thou dooſt it, it will come out, &amp; thou ſhalt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenged with ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhame: I am thy huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds déereſt friend, with whom I am daily conuerſant, and dooſt thou thinke I could find in my hart, to offer him ſuch iniury? no: &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> art not thou more to blame, that being y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wife of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, wilt betray thy huſband, who is déerer to thée then all friends? fie vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thée vild woman, fare thée wel &amp; ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d: I wil not yet tell thy huſband, vnleſſe I ſpie thée prooue light, but I ſhall neuer thinke well of thée while I liue: &amp; with y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he opened y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chamber doore, &amp; the cobler chopt in, &amp; taking y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſmith by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hand, ſaid, neighbor, I thank you for your good cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel, I haue hard al the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> paſt
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:10138:18"/> betwéene you and my wife, and truelie: and with that the Cobler wept, I am heartily glad I haue ſuch a truſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie friend, to whom in my abſence at any time, becauſe my mother is an old woman, I commit the ouerſight of my wife: and truely neighbour quoth hee, I pray you thinke neuer the worſe of hir, for ſhe told me the whole matter, &amp; appointed me to ſtand at the doore, that when you ſhould haue offered hir any diſcurteſie, I might haue ruſht in and haue taken you: ſo that I perceiue you are as honeſt as ſhe, and ſhe as honeſt as you, and that your meanings were both a like. I am glad of that quoth the Smith, that you haue ſo vertuous a wife, I hope I haue done the part of a fréend, to pleaſure my neighbour: you haue doone ſo quoth the Cobler, and therefore ere we part, wéele drinke a quart of wine. So the Cobler be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed good chéere on the Smith, and euer after accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him for his friend, and whenſoeuer he went out of towne, committed the charge of his wife to the Smith, who at all times had frée egreſſe and regreſſe to the Cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers houſe without ſuſpition.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>This tale of the Smith made al the company to laugh, and the cobler he was ſtarke mad for anger, ſaying, that if it had béene his caſe, he would haue giuen him wine with a cudgell: tuſh Cobler quoth the Smith, neuer thinke but our art can ſurpaſſe yours in ſuch wenching matters, and that a Smith can ſooner make a Cobler a Cuckold, then a Cobler a Smith: vpon this they fell to iarres, &amp; from words had falne to blowes, if they of the Barge had not parted them: ſo at laſt they were quiet, and made friends. And then the Cobler he began to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate that they would go forward in their merry exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, wherevpon a gentleman ſitting by ſaid; maiſters, it is ſo good to paſſe away the time, that to continue ſo honeſt a ſport, I will be next: and thus therefore I will deſcribe him.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:10138:18"/>
               <head>¶The deſcription of the Gentleman.</head>
               <l>HIs ſtature was of a middle length,</l>
               <l>VVell ioynted, of a good ſtrength,</l>
               <l>Siken writtes report to vs</l>
               <l>VVas that Troian Troilus:</l>
               <l>For hee was of comely viſage,</l>
               <l>And his manners of curteous vſage.</l>
               <l>His haire in curled lockes hung downe,</l>
               <l>And well I wot the coloure was nutbrowne:</l>
               <l>And yet it was ful bright and ſheene,</l>
               <l>Such wore Paris I weene:</l>
               <l>VVhen he ſailed to Grecia</l>
               <l>To fetch the faire Helena.</l>
               <l>His front was of a ſyluer hue,</l>
               <l>Powdred thicke with vaines blue.</l>
               <l>His eies were lumynous,</l>
               <l>Chriſtallyne and beauteous:</l>
               <l>Gray and ſparkling like the ſtarres,</l>
               <l>VVhen the day her light vp ſparres.</l>
               <l>His cheekes like the Lilies white,</l>
               <l>Or as Luna being bright:</l>
               <l>And yet comely therevpon,</l>
               <l>VVas ſhadowed colour Vermilion:</l>
               <l>That gaſers all woulden ſuppoſe,</l>
               <l>How the Lilie and the Roſe,</l>
               <l>Did maken warre each with other,</l>
               <l>VVhich ſhould be aboue an other.</l>
               <l>His ſuercoate was of Satten blew,</l>
               <l>Like vnto a louer true:</l>
               <l>His hoſe were garded along,</l>
               <l>VVith many a broad veluet thong.</l>
               <l>His Cloake grew large and ſide,</l>
               <l>And a faire whinyard by his ſide.</l>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:10138:19"/>
               <l>The pummell guilt: and on his head</l>
               <l>He had a bonnet colour read:</l>
               <l>An alder leefer ſwaine I weene,</l>
               <l>In the barge there was not ſeene:</l>
               <l>And then thus he gan tell,</l>
               <l>What in Cambridge to a ſcholler befell.</l>
               <div type="tale">
                  <head>¶The Gentlemans tale. Conteining the contrarie fortunes that a Scholler of Cambridge had in his Loues.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the Vniuerſitie of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> in <hi>Peters</hi> Hoſtell, there liued a Scholler famous for his learning, called <hi>Rowland,</hi> who beeing placſt there by his friends, ſo profited, that he grew to be one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> felowes of the houſe, being in great eſtimation for the honeſty of his life, and the excellencie of his learning: he was a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as well pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portioned as he was qualified: and had as well <hi>bona corporis,</hi> as he had <hi>bona animi,</hi> and could as well play the wag and the wanton abroad, as he could applie his Bookes and ſtudie at home: amorous he was, and one that delighted to féede his eye with euery faire face, which after returned to his great preiudice, thus. It for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuned one day in the Summer ſeaſon, that for recreation he walked as farre as <hi>Cherryhinton,</hi> to eate a meſſe of Creame, where being very pleaſant, as hee ſat ieſting with his Hoſteſſe; there came in a Gentlemans daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the towne, a maide of excéeding beautie, ſo well proportioned in the lineaments of hir face, that nature ſéemed to try in hir an experiment of hir cunning. This girle, as wiſe as ſhe was faire, and as wanton as ſhee was wittie, came in and queſtioned with the hoſteſſe about ſome buſineſſe: <hi>Rowland</hi> ſéeing ſuch a Nymphe come ſwéeping in, thought eyther <hi>Venus</hi> or <hi>Diana</hi> had
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:10138:19"/> come in their Country wéedes to bewitch mens fancies: he caſt his eie vpon the excellencie of hir phiſnomy with ſuch a piercing looke, that Loue entring by the eie, ſo wroong him at the heart, that forſooth fancie hir of force he muſt.</p>
                  <p>Nowe my young Scholler coulde doe nothing but gaze vppon hir, for Court hir hee coulde not, vnleſſe hee ſhould haue begun to wooe hir with ſome wordes of Art, or ſome Axiomes of Philoſophie. The young Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman ſeeing the Scholler looke ſo earneſtly vppon hir, beganne to bluſh, and ſo taking hir leaue of the Hoſteſſe went hir way. The Scholler ſéeing hir going out of doores, thought of the old prouerbe: Faint heart neuer woone faire Lady. And therefore called to hir thus: Faire Gentlewoman quoth he, you may ſée we Schollers haue litle maners, that holding the pot in our hands will not make ſuch a ſwéete ſaint as you drinke: howe ſay you Gentlewoman, will it pleaſe you to pledge mee? The wily wench hearing ſuch a Schollerlike gratulation, ſéeing by this ſalute, that Schollers had read of Loue, more then they coulde ſay of Loue: and though they coulde tell what was Latine for a faire woman, yet could neither woe hir, nor winne hir, turned backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and with a lowe curteſie thanked him. Hee off with his corner Cappe (for hee was a Batcheler in Artes) and with a glauncing looke drunke to hir: Shée like a wanton, pledgde him with a ſmile. <hi>Row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> at this taking heart at graſſe, ſtept to hir, and tooke hir by the hande: beginning thus to holde hir in chat.</p>
                  <p>Your Towne here (forſooth) of <hi>Cherryhinton,</hi> hath made me oft play the trewa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to come hither for cherries: and as mine Hoſtes can tel, full many a meſſe of creame haue I eaten in hir houſe: for we ſchollers are good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, &amp; loue to be pleaſant: eſpecially if we might haue the company of ſuch faire Gentlewomen as your ſelfe:
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:10138:20"/> Therefore Miſtres, if I chaunce to come to towne to eat a pound of cherries (if I may be ſo bold) I would trouble you to take part with mee; and if I méete you at <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> the beſt wine in the Towne ſhall bee your wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come: the wench (that had much adooe to kéepe hir counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance) thought to féede him vp with faire ſpéeches, till ſhée made him as fatte as a foole, and therefore made him this reply. Truely ſyr indéede many ſchollers come to <hi>Cherryhinton</hi> to eate cherries: but ſyr, you are the firſt man that euer I dranke withall, for ſchollers bee ſo full of their learning, and fine tearmes, that Country wen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches cannot vnderſtande them, but I for my part at the firſt ſight like of you ſo well, that if my leiſure ſerue, whenſoeuer you come and pleaſe to ſend for mee, I will as long as I dare beare you company, but nowe forſooth time cals mee away and I muſt bee gone. With all my heart quoth <hi>Rowland,</hi> but truely wee muſt not part without a kiſſe, which ſhée willingly tooke at his hands, and went home: where aſſoone as ſhée came, ſhee reuealed all to a young gentleman that lay in hir Fathers houſe, who was ſure to hir: they laughing heartily at the ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers Courting, and reſoluing to make good ſport with him ere they had done. But <hi>Rowland</hi> he that thought e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſmile was a fancie, and euery maide that laught on him, loued him, coniectured aſſuredly by the familiar curteſie of the gentlewoman, that ſhée was greatly affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionate towards him: whereupon he began to inquire of his Hoſteſſe whoſe daughter ſhée was, of what wealth hir Father was, what children he had, and what Dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie the maide was like to haue to hir portion, as a man reſolued the woman was already woone, becauſe ſhée had giuen him ſuch gracious fauours. The Hoſteſſe as well as ſhée could tolde him all: which done, he paide his ſhot, and went to <hi>Cambridge,</hi> where he began altogether to muſe on the beauty of his Miſtres, and to lay an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth plots in his head what were beſt to be done: at laſt
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:10138:20"/> he reſolued to ſend a letter to hir, to ſignifie his loue: or elſe to go himſelfe, &amp; to carry two or thrée of his fellows with him, and ſo to diſcourſe vnto hir howe he loued hir; but at laſt hee fully determined with himſelfe to write vnto hir: wherefore taking pen and inke in hande, hee wrote a letter to hir to this effect.</p>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <head>Rowlands Letter to the faire Maide of Cherryhinton.</head>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>MIſtres <hi>Marian,</hi>
                           </salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> the great Philoſopher, for all his wit was in loue with <hi>Hermia:</hi> and <hi>Socrates</hi> the ſage, could not ſo farre ſubdue his paſſions, but that he fell in feakes with <hi>Zantippa:</hi> Schollers as they reade much of loue, ſo when they once fall in loue, there is no ho with them till they haue their Loue. The fineſt glaſſe is moſt brittle, and the beſt Schollers ſooneſt ouergon with fancy. For an inſtance, was not <hi>Ouid</hi> as déepe in loue, as he was excellent in learning? I bring in theſe compariſons Miſtres <hi>Marian,</hi> becauſe the other Sonday being at <hi>Cherryhinton,</hi> and ſéeing your ſwéete ſelfe, I was ſo ouertaken with your beauty and good behauior, that euer ſince the remembrance of your face could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer out of my fancie: nor, I thinke, neuer ſhall, although I ſhould be drencht in the forgetfull flouds of <hi>Lethe.</hi> Sée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then my affection is ſo great, I pray you conſider of me, and be not ſo vnkinde, but let me haue loue for loue: and though here in the vniuerſitie you ſée me ſimple, yet my Parents at home are men of good parentage, &amp; what I want in wealth, I ſhall ſupply in Learning: ponder with your ſelfe, and reade but the liues and anſweres of the Philoſophers, and ſée howe they vſed their wiues, with what curteſie, how euer the women were the moſt Maiſters, and had the Soueraignty, which they deſire. Thus hoping you will conſider of my Loue; deſiring you to ſend me an anſwer, I bid you farewell.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Yours in duſt and aſhes, Rowland.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:10138:21"/>
                  <p>When hee had thus finiſhed his letter, hee thought to ſhew him ſelfe ſomewhat poeticall, and thought a letter was not worth a ruſh, vnleſſe there were ſome verſes at the latter end, and there he affixed as a poſtſcript this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marousditty.</p>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="song">
                     <body>
                        <head>Rowlands ſong to his Miſtres.</head>
                        <lg>
                           <l>AProach in place Pierides,</l>
                           <l>My vaine in verſes to bend:</l>
                           <l>Dame Chryſeis which gauſt Homer ſucke,</l>
                           <l>Thy tender teats me lend.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Alcmena thou which Ioue didſt rocke,</l>
                           <l>In cradle full of ioy:</l>
                           <l>Eke ſwath me in thoſe ſwadling clowtes,</l>
                           <l>Account me for thy boy.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Ye Naiades and pretty Nymphs,</l>
                           <l>That on Pernaſſus dwell:</l>
                           <l>Lend me your Muſe that I may now,</l>
                           <l>My Miſtres beauty tell.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>How that in beautie ſhee doth paſſe</l>
                           <l>Venus the Queene of Loue:</l>
                           <l>To whom, if I doe gaine hir grace,</l>
                           <l>I will be Turtle Doue.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Therefore my deere conceiue my griefe,</l>
                           <l>And thinke how I doe loue thee:</l>
                           <l>And in ſome lines ſend me reliefe,</l>
                           <l>For time and truth ſhall proue me.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Thus hoping pen and paper ſhall</l>
                           <l>Thy minde to me ſhort tell:</l>
                           <l>But loue me as I doe loue thee,</l>
                           <l>And ſo my deere farewell.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:10138:21"/>
                  <p>THus hauing both finiſhed his letter and his verſes, he ſent them by a conuenient meſſenger the next Sat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terday to <hi>Cherryhinton,</hi> and that forſooth was his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteſſe: who very orderly ſent for the gentlewoman to hir houſe, and deliuered the letters to hir, with earneſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations from ſyr <hi>Rowland.</hi> The gentlewoman in outward ſhewe ſéemed to accept them as gratefully, as he ſent them louingly, and ſo hied hir home: where pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ſhée called for hir newe betrothed huſband, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gentlemen hir friends, and reuealed vnto them how ſhée had receiued letters from hir newe louer the Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler. All they flocked about hir, to heare what excellent ſtuffe was conteined in ſo learned a mans letters: but when they heard him howe like a Philoſophicall foole he writ: they all in a ſynode peremptorily concluded, that the greateſt Clarkes were not the wiſeſt men: and I maruaile of that quoth one of the company, for two rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: forthe one I haue heard this old ſaid ſaw, that Loue makes men Oratours and affection whetteth on elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence: Secondly, there was none more amorous then <hi>Ouid</hi> (yet a profound ſcholler) inſomuch that he writ thrée bookes <hi>De Arte Amandi,</hi> and ſo did <hi>Anacreon Tibullus,</hi> &amp; <hi>Propertius.</hi> I but quoth an other, as they were ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, ſo were they well brought vp in the Court, and knew as many externall manners, as they did inwarde principles: but ware my Maiſters, when a ſcholler is once brought vp in the Vniuerſities, and hath no other bringing vp but plaine <hi>Ergo</hi> to plod in, nor conuerſeth with none but his bookes, and then hap to fall in Loue: truſt me he will bee as ignorant to wooe, as the plough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to diſpute, thinking that womens fancies are woon with Figures, and their thoughts ouerreacht with the quiddities of Art: but of all that euer I heard write, this ſetteth downe his minde the moſt ſimply: and therefore quoth <hi>Marian</hi> ſhall hee be anſwerd as fooliſhly, for I my ſelfe will be Secretary. Nay quoth diuers of the gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:10138:22"/> wee will put in our verdict with you: No quoth ſhée, trie but a womans witte: thats knauiſh enough quoth one of them: and ſo ſtepping to hir ſtandiſh ſhée wrote thus.</p>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <head>Marian of Cherryhinton to Syr Rowland of Cambridge, health.</head>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>SWéete ſyr <hi>Rowland,</hi>
                           </salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>I receiued your Letters, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I perceiue that Schollers in loue are like to a Sow with pig vnder an Apple trée, which either haſtily muſt haue a crab, or elſe looſe their Litter. If I bring in a Country compariſon blame mee not, in that I am a Country wench, and haue none but plaine Country lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicke, but howſoeuer I write, I meane well. Indéede rightly you ſay, that the fineſt glaſſe is moſt brittle, and the beſt Schollers ſooneſt pinched with Loue, which I thinke to bee true: for aſſoone as euer I ſawe you, howe your eies waited vpon my face, as an obiect of your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, I tooke you to be too wiſe, kinde, and amorous: and therefore ſéeing euer ſince you haue béene paſſionate, it were great pitty that you ſhoulde not haue for your paines (euen as wee vſe in a homely prouerbe) a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try ſackefull of loue: and the rather you induce mee to thinke well of you, that you bring in the examples of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotle</hi> and <hi>Hermia,</hi> and of <hi>Socrates</hi> and <hi>Zantippa:</hi> whereby you ſéeme to promiſe, that I ſhall as they had, inioy the ſoueraignty; and that if I be like them in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, you will be as ſuffering as they in patience: yet will I neither be ſo proude towards you as <hi>Hermia,</hi> for ſhée ridde <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> with a ſnaffle like a horſe: nor ſo waſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh as <hi>Zantippa,</hi> for ſhe crownd <hi>Socrates</hi> with a Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berpot, but betwéene both: and ſo wiſhing you to hope the beſt, I bid you farewell.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Yours neuer if not euer, Marian of Cherryhinton.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:10138:22"/>
                  <p>After ſhée had done hir letter, that ſhée might ſéeme to be no whit behinde him in any good will: ſhée leaned hir head on hir hand, and in a Poeticall furie writ hir Louer theſe verſes.</p>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="poem">
                     <body>
                        <head>Marians verſes to Syr Rowland.</head>
                        <lg>
                           <l>FEare not my deare the ſtormes of Loue,</l>
                           <l>for they are paſſing ſower:</l>
                           <l>And ſometimes ſweete as honycombe,</l>
                           <l>and all within an hower.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Like to a Sunſhine Sommers daie,</l>
                           <l>When Phoebus ſhewes amaine:</l>
                           <l>And yet ere night from tawnie Clowdes,</l>
                           <l>doe fall a ſhowre of raine.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>So whatſoeuer chance betide,</l>
                           <l>or whatſoeuer fall:</l>
                           <l>If Father frowne, or Mother chide,</l>
                           <l>yet muſt you beare withall.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>For why? the Cuckow doth not come</l>
                           <l>in Aprill more ſure,</l>
                           <l>Then I will fixe my loue on thee,</l>
                           <l>for euer to indure.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Thus wiſhing thee to thinke of me,</l>
                           <l>in ſtudie or in ſtreete,</l>
                           <l>I bid you heartilie farewell,</l>
                           <l>till we in Cambridge meete.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:10138:23"/>
                  <p>HAuing thus ended hir ſong and the Letter, ſhée calde the Conuocation of the merry gentlemen, &amp; ſhewed them hir humour in proſe, and hir vaine in verſe: aſking if ſhée had done it knauiſhly enough? I quoth hir betro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed huſband, and ſo excéedingly well, that you ſhall ſtand for foure and twenty knaues till Chriſtmas next. Tuſh quoth an other, womens wittes are like Shef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fielde kniues, for they are ſometimes ſo kéene as they will cutte a haire, and ſometimes ſo blunt that they muſt goe to the grindſtone: That is (quoth the ſecond) when you perſwade them to ſilence or obedience, talke with them but in that doctrine, and they are méere dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
                  <p>Thus they began to deſcant of womens wit, but the gentlewoma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wily enough, left them all, &amp; went &amp; laid vp hir letters till Saterday market: Then ſhée went to his Hoſtes, &amp; deliuered the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to hir, earneſtly intreating hir, if ſhée ſaw ſyr Rowland, to conuey that packet vnto him. The Hoſteſſe promiſed hir to doe it faithfully, and effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually: and away to Cambridge ſhée went, where ſcarſe ſhée was ſet with hir butter and hir milke, but ſhée ſpied ſyr <hi>Rowland</hi> come flinging downe the Market hill, in his wide ſléeude Gowne, and his corner Cap: ſhée néede not to call him, for hee ſtraight found hir out, and ſhée as ſoone deliuered him the packet: ſyr <hi>Rowland</hi> thankt hir, and away hee went to his ſtudie to reade the contents: but it was too farre to <hi>Peters Hoſtell,</hi> and therefore hee calde in at a Tauerne by the way for a pint of wine, and there he opened the letter, which when hee had read, hee perceiued by the contents ſhée loued him: for hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſimple, perceiued not howe ſhée bobde foole with him: but taking euery ieſt for a ſentence, hee thought himſelfe the Maiſter of all worldly content, and that Fortune coulde not aduaunce him higher on hir whéele, then to haue ſo faire a Maide to his Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour. Then he viewed ouer hir verſes, &amp; in a great paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:10138:23"/> praiſed hir Poetry, commended hir wit, ſaying: for ſtature ſhe was <hi>Iuno,</hi> for beautie <hi>Venus,</hi> for learning and qualities <hi>Pallas:</hi> thus in meditation of his letter and his loue, ſat poore ſir <hi>Rowland,</hi> from eight a clocke till eleauen, and then hearing the Hoſtell Bell ring to din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, for feare he ſhould loaſe his halfepenny chops, he put his letter into his pocket, and went his way. After dinner, he fell to his old vaine: got alone to be ſolitarie, &amp; then ſat ruminating on the good ſucceſſe of his loues, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compting it rather to his profeſſion, then his fortune, for he thought none ſo faire, chaſte, nor riche, but a Scholler might win with his Logick. Thus he paſſed ouer day by day in ſending of letters to his loue, and diuers times reſorting thither, but ſeldome could he ſpeake with hir, for that ſhe fained ſome excuſe; onely when ſhe ment to laugh, then ſhe was for his company. But it fell out that one Satterday aboue the reſt, that ſir <hi>Rowland</hi> met hir in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and finding hir with other hir neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, ſaluted hir, and would néedes welcome hir to the towne with a pinte of Wine, which ſhe tooke very kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that ſhe might ſooth him vp ſtill in his vaine hope, and forſooth to the Tauerne ſhée and her companions went with him, where they had good game at our <hi>Cambridge</hi> wooer: but <hi>Marian</hi> taking him aſide, told him that hir fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and hir mother had intelligence of their loues, and as farre as ſhe could coniecture, it was by his hoſteſſe: therefore ſhe wild him not to make her priuie to his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets any more, nor to come to <hi>Cherryhinton</hi> but when ſhe ſent for him, which ſhould be as ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as opportunity would ſerue, hoping though hir father now were not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, yet in time he would conſent, &amp; eſpecially, if he ſaw him Maiſter of Arts: with this the Scholler reſted ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and they dranke their wine and departed. Thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene them paſſed on all the Summer, till the déepe of winter, about Chriſtmas, when ſhée on a time &amp; the reſt of the Gentlemen, deſirous to be pleaſant, determined to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:10138:24"/> haue ſome ſport with the Scholler, and ſo cauſed <hi>Marian</hi> to ſend a Letter for him, that he ſhould come that night and ſpeake with her: which ſhe did; and he poore ſoule no ſooner receiued it, but in all haſt hied him in the froſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie euening to <hi>Cherryhinton:</hi> where when he came, hee ſtraight ſpoke with <hi>Marian,</hi> &amp; ſhe wiſht him to ſtay in an old Barne while her Father was at ſupper, and then ſhe would conuey him into a baſe court, where he ſhould walke hard vnder her chamber doore, and then when her father were to bed, ſhe would let him in. The Scholler ſtood there a while, and <hi>Marian</hi> came ſtraight &amp; conduc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him into a ſquare court, where <hi>Rowland</hi> reſted him till hir father ſhould go to bed. The night grew darke, and with that paſſing colde, ſo that <hi>Rowland</hi> waxed we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his ſtanding, and wiſht that her father were in bed: there ſtood the poore Scholler ſhaking and trembling in his ioynts, till it was eleuen of the clocke: then ſaw he a light at the doore, and he heard <hi>Marian</hi> cal him: oh bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed houre thought he, that now I ſhall both go to a good fier, and to my Louer. Sir <hi>Rowland</hi> (quoth ſhe) be ſtill a while, my father and mother is gone to bed, but my bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and two Gentlemen more are vp at Cardes, &amp; they haue but a ſet to play, and then they will to their reſt: alas ſwéete heart (quoth he) I am almoſt ſterued for cold, yet the hope that I haue to enioy thy preſence, doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort me, that I take all things with patience. The Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen that ſtood hard by and hard all this, laught at the ſcholler, and vp they went againe to their chamber to be merry: but ſtill walkt poore <hi>Rowland,</hi> beating his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds about him for cold, and expecting ſtill when his Louer ſhould cal him: wel there he trauerſt his ground ſtil like a <hi>pery-patetian,</hi> and only had the ſight of the heauens to contemplate, till it was about one of the clock, and then came they all downe againe to laugh: &amp; aſſoone as he ſaw the candle at the chinke of the doore, he began to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted, &amp; came thither, ſhaking &amp; beating of his téeth ſo
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:10138:24"/> ſore, that he could not ſpeake. Where are you ſwéet hart (quoth ſhe) alas how ſorry am I for thy diſtreſſe, thinke that the heart in my belly is as colde for gréefe as thy ioints are with the froſt, faine would I haue thée come in, but the looſers will not part play, and ſo they ſit ſtill, therefore I hope thou wilt weigh my credit. Oh <hi>Marian</hi> (quoth he) &amp; his téeth ſo iarred one againſt another, that they could ſcarſe vnderſtand him, I am like to periſh with cold, yet were it twiſe as froſtie, &amp; the night thriſe as long, I would walke héere, rather then procure thy diſparagement: gramercie ſwéet loue (quoth ſhe) &amp; with that ſhe bid him be ſtill a while, &amp; the Gentlemen all fell a laughing to heare how kinde a foole the Scholler was, and with what patience, he bid his pennance: oh, quoth the one of them, this is but an experiment of his Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophicall principles, for he reades in <hi>Tully:</hi>
                     <q xml:lang="lat">Non oportet ſapientem in aduerſis dolore concidere.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I (quoth the ſecond) and <hi>Mimus Publius</hi> giues him this counſell:
<q xml:lang="lat">Aduerſis te proba, vt fortunam, cum neceſſe fuerit, patienter inſultantem feras.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>You ſay well (quoth the third,) but let him for mee make an inſtance of himſelfe for ſuch axiomes, I wil ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be a warme foole, then ſo colde a Philoſopher. This they gan deſcant vppon the poore Schollers myſerie, till the clock ſtroake thrée, and then as they were comming downe, they heard a noiſe at the doore, which was this poore <hi>Rowland</hi> créeping vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhade for warmth, his téeth beating ſo lowd, that they might heare them eaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vp the ſtaires, all this mooued not my yoong Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſe to pittie, but increaſt their laughter. Aſſoone as hee heard them come downe the ſtaires, almoſt dead,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:10138:25"/> he cald out, who is there: oh ſwéet heart, it is thy <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian,</hi> quoth ſhée? Then for Gods ſake quoth <hi>Rowland,</hi> take pittie of my life, for I am almoſt dead, doo but open the doore, and let me ſit héere vpon the ſtaires, that I may haue ſome ſhelter from the cold. Alas quoth ſhe ſwéete loue, thou ſhalt and thou wilt: but when the dore is opened, it makes ſuch a noyſe, that it wakens the whole houſe. Rather, quoth he, let me ſuffer death, then you be diſcredited, for if I were to abide the ſtone of <hi>Siſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus,</hi> the whéele of <hi>Ixion,</hi> the gripe of <hi>Prometheus,</hi> &amp; the hunger of <hi>Tantalus,</hi> yet had I rather pocket vp all theſe tortures with patience, then bring thy credit within the compaſſe of the leaſt preiudice: at this period ſhe left him, and vp they went, ſmiling at the conſtancie of <hi>Rowland.</hi> The Gentlemen they were ſléepie, and went to bed, and <hi>Marian,</hi> as far as I can coniecture, though it were ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what before the mariage, that night made triall of hir new betrothed huſband, where from thrée, ſhe lay with him till ſix, and then it waxed day light, and ſhe roſe; and remembring her louer went downe, opened the doore, and found him almoſt ſenceleſſe: there wiping hir eyes, as though ſhee had wept, ſhee perſwaded him that ſhee was the moſt ſorrowfull woman in the world for his ſharpe froſtie night he had ſuffered, proteſting ſhe was falne into an ague, for very feare &amp; gréefe ſhe had taken to ſée him in ſuch diſtreſſe, &amp; could by no meanes redreſſe it: but good <hi>Rowland</hi> (quoth ſhee) be content, hie thée to <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and take ſome hot broaths, leaſt by this meanes thou fall into a ſickneſſe, &amp; then for very ſorrow I dye: no quoth <hi>Rowland,</hi> &amp; he could ſcarſe ſpeake or go, feare not me, for the hope of thy after fauours, will be a ſufficient comfort for me: and with that taking his leaue for his cold nights worke he had a kiſſe, and ſo departed. Wel as weak as he was, home he ſcambled, &amp; got to his chamber, &amp; diſcouered to a friend of his, how he was like to periſh of an extreame cold he had take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if he did not ſo
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:10138:25"/> much for him as to get him a Phiſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: who ſtraight we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and brought him a Doctor, that with inward potions and outward oyles and vnguents ſo wrought him, that hee recouered him to his former health, although verie hardly: for he was ſo froſen in his loines, and ſo nipped in the muſkells and ſynewes, that if his Phyſition had not bene good, he had periſhed. It was almoſt a quarter of a yeare before <hi>Rowland</hi> was frolick againe: in which time <hi>Marian</hi> thinking ſhe had loſt hir louer with a nut, ſent him a preſent of apples to winne him againe, which he receiued ſo gratefullie that he valewed the worſt of them worth a felowſhip, eating them with ſuch an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarie taſt, that hee imagined them as ſweet as <hi>Ambroſia,</hi> and all for that they came from his <hi>Marian.</hi> Thus continued <hi>Rowland</hi> in his amorous humour vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till ſuch time as <hi>Marian</hi> forſooth muſt be maried: and for that it was aduent, there was no aſking in the church, but they procured a licenſe the day before. As ſhee and the reſt of hir friends which were inuited to the nupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als were merilie ieſting, oh Lord (quoth ſhee) I had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt forgot my ſelfe, to morrow muſt be the wedding, and the bride is at Cambridge: why gentlemen it were no bargaine if <hi>Rowland</hi> were not here: therefore quoth ſhe, I will ſend for him, and lay ſuch a plotte that hee ſhall be with vs all dinner, &amp; yet taſt none of our meat. I pray you quoth her huſband, let vs ſée your cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning in that. Alas quoth one of the gentlemen, poore <hi>Rowland</hi> is credulous, and whatſoeuer miſtres <hi>Marian</hi> ſaith, hée thinks it is Goſpel: but if he wil be ſo ſimple as to think that his laſt nights worke is not a ſufficient warning, hée is worthie of what ſo euer befalles. Well, vpon this <hi>Marian</hi> ſent for him, and come hée did in the euening, where, to make my tale ſhort, ſhe made him walk in his wonted ſtatie till one of the clocke: then ſhe let him into a good fire, where he well warmed him ſelfe, and ſhe lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uingly ſate by him, diſcourſing of the laſt nightes worke
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:10138:26"/> that he abode ſo patientlie: at laſt ſhe commaunded the maide to lay the cloth that they might haue ſome <hi>quel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que choſe</hi> for a readie ſupper, which they went buſilie about: for <hi>Rowland</hi> ſaid he was verie hungrie. As the cloth was laid, and they readie to ſit downe the wench came running in, and ſaid, that hir Maiſter was riſing, and ſéeing the light of the fier was comming into the Parlor. Alas what ſhal I do quoth <hi>Maria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?</hi> hide me ſome where quoth <hi>Rowland</hi> whiles he be gone to bed. Come quoth ſhe, here ſtands a new truncke and a large, come, ſkippe into it, and I will for a while rake vp the fire and goe to bed while the old man be fallen a ſléepe: with that <hi>Rowland</hi> whipt into the truncke, and ſhe lockt him in, &amp; ſtraight in a pleaſant humor went to hir new huſband, where ſhee lay al night, and left <hi>Rowland</hi> ſafe ſhut vp for ſtarting. Still laie hée expecting when ſhe ſhould come, but hearing nothing, extremely wearie for verie griefe hee fell a ſléepe till the next morning. When the poore ſcholler awakt and entred into conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration where he was, he began to be halfe in ſuſpition that he was mockt and abuſed, ſtill he lay patiently till hee heard them of the houſe ſay, God morrow miſtres <hi>Marian,</hi> God ſend you a good day, to day the Sun ſhines faire, you ſhal haue a cléere daie to your wedding. This word went as cold to his hart as a knife, that <hi>Marian</hi> ſhould be maried, he made a foole to ſuffer ſuch diſparag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his credit: yet as before he was patient in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treames, and ſo reſolued with content to ſee the ſucceſſe of his abuſe. Well to Church goe the bridegrome and the bride with all their friendes attendants, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried they were with great ſolemnitie: this done, home they came to dinner, and after they were ſet and placed in the parlor where this truncke ſtoode, they fell to their viads which were verie ſumptuous. The gentlemen bidding reach downe the pigge, the capen, gooſe, ſwan, turkey, pheſant, biter, veniſon, and ſuch daintie cates:
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:10138:26"/> all this hard <hi>Rowland,</hi> and being paſſing hungrie, wiſhed he had a legge of the worſt of them in his hand; ſtill hée ſtoode almoſt famiſhed and ſmothered till the tables were taken vp, and the boards ſhifted, and they fell to dauncing. All this heard <hi>Rowland,</hi> and hearing the muſicke fell a ſléepe vntill ſupper time, and then hee awakt, and heard how they laid the tables and went to ſupper where they were paſſing pleaſant, and the more for that they ment to make ſport with <hi>Rowland</hi> after ſupper was done, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued not long, for they made the more haſt for that they ment to be merrie. When the cloth was taken vp the Bride fetcht a great ſigh: what wife quoth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grome, why ſigh you? in a dumpe? repent you of the match? no quoth ſhée, but I haue a blot in my conſcience, and now before you all I meane to reueale it. I was once beloued of a Cambridge ſcholler, who loued me in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tierlie and ſuffred much for my ſake: then from point to point ſhee recompted vnto them the whole diſcourſe of the loues and fortunes paſſed betweene <hi>Row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and hir, whereat the companie had good ſport.</p>
                  <p>A man hee was quoth ſhée, wiſe, proper, and well proportioned: and for proofe hould the key, open the truncke quoth ſhée, and I will ſhew you his picture. <hi>Rowland</hi> hearing this, armd himſelfe to ſuffer al: and ſo the truncke was opened &amp; he roſe out like <hi>Lazarus</hi> from his graue. Good Lord quoth the companie, what is this a ſpirit? <hi>In nomine Ieſus vnde venis? E purgatorio</hi> quoth <hi>Rowland.</hi> And with that all the companie laught while they could ſit. At laſt when they were wearie with laughing <hi>Rowland</hi> had ſilence, hee boldlie ſaid: thus I am glad gentlemen that my miſhap hath made you ſo merrie, and that miſtres bride hath ſo large a plaine ſong to runne deſcant on; <hi>Caueat Emptor:</hi> this is but a comedie, but looke for a tragedie when ſoeuer it falles. And ſo he went out of the doore ſore aſhamed that hee
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:10138:27"/> had ſuch a kindlie ſcoffe. The companie laught well, and hee patientlie went home thinking how fortunate a man hee ſhould be, if he might liue to reuenge. <hi>Row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> at this miſfortune had an inſight into the world and began to waxe wiſer, that in ſhort time he became to haue as much knowledge in worldlie affaires as in his booke, and was for his good behauiour and pleaſant witte highlie had in eſtimation, not onelie amongeſt ſchollers, but amongeſt towneſmen, that in all the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſitie he was called the gentlemanlike ſcholler. Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing thus in good credit, and yet diſcontented, becauſe Fortune fauoured him with no oportunitie to reuenge: it ſo fell out at length that <hi>Marian</hi> comming euerie wéeke to Cambridge, eſpied among the ſchollers one whom ſhe caſt hir eie on, and thought him the propereſt man in the whole Vniuerſitie: Well, ſhée counted it but a glaunce, and thought as lightly to paſſe it ouer as it ſleightly entred: for ſhée found loue, that though he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred in by graunt of courteſie, yet hee would not bee thruſt out by force of extremitie, in ſo much that ſhee could not content hirſelfe without, but with the fight of hir new friend, which was done ſo manifeſtlie that the ſcholler perceiued it, and aiming at the faireſt, one Satterday ſéeing hir in the market offred hir a quart of wine, which ſhe tooke verie gratefully, and began to bee verie familiar with him, in ſo much that before they paſt, force of loue made her ſo ſhameleſſe, that ſhe was content to yéeld to his requeſt, ſo that time and place would ſerue without the diſparagment of hir credite.</p>
                  <p>Vpon this they concluded, that maiſter <hi>Awdrey</hi> (for ſo wee wil call him) ſhould grow familiar with hir huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and by that meanes ſhould hee haue a better meanes to the quieting of his minde. Vpon this deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination they departed, and hee ſo brought it to paſſe, that not onlie he was acquainted with hir huſband but verie familiar, that he would carrie maiſter <hi>Awdrey</hi>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:10138:27"/> often from Cambridge with him to Cherryhinton, and I hope you do imagin hee was no little welcome gueſt to his wife. Being thus fitted in their paſſions onely watching for place, lingring off the time at laſt it was concluded, that ſhe ſhould come on a Satterday to Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge, and faine to ſtay with a kinſwoman of hirs that dwelt in the towne, and ſo lie with hir all night: this ſtood for a ſentence, and ſo the next weeke was decreed. In the mean time it ſo fel out, that maiſter <hi>Awdrey</hi> and ſir <hi>Rowland</hi> being of great acquaintance, and ſuch pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate familiars that nothing was holden too ſecret be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene them, maiſter <hi>Awdrey</hi> ſmothering this ioy in himſelfe, thought to partake it with his friend: and ſo as he and ſir <hi>Rowland</hi> were walking reuealed vnto him the loue that had paſt betwéene him and <hi>Marian,</hi> and on ſatterday was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> night when his <hi>poſſe</hi> ſhould come into <hi>eſſe,</hi> deſiring him to tel him wher he might haue a houſe fit for ſuch a purpoſe. Sir <hi>Rowla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</hi> hearing this ſmylde, which made M. <hi>Awdrey</hi> to inquire y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe of his laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: wherupon ſitting down vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> graſſe he bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count vnto him the whole diſcourſe of his loues with <hi>Marian,</hi> &amp; what ſundry abuſes he ſuffered at hir hand, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great &amp; vtter infamy of ſchollers. M. <hi>Audrey</hi> hearing this, ſat a great while in a muſe, at laſt he ſaid, and wil women be Crocodiles? to wéepe roſe water &amp; vineger at one time, ſtill to dally in extremes, to loue without rea-, ſon &amp; hate without cauſe? oh the folly of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be ſuch to ſuch painted ſepulchers, whoſe painted ſheaths hold lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den blades, whoſe ſkins are glorious like pa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>thers, but haue deuouring pa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ches. By that God that drew that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate femal fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that forefortunat <hi>Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> I hate hir as extremely as I loued her earneſtly: and I wil not onely yéeld y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> oportunity to reue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, but I wil ioyne iſſue with thee to perform it to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vttermoſt. At this <hi>Rowla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</hi> was tickled with inward ioy, &amp; taking <hi>Awdrey</hi> in his arms proteſted ſuch hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble ſeruice for that friendlie promiſe,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:10138:28"/> as euer ſhould lye in his abilitie to execute. Thus in this determination of reuenge they croſt the fieldes to Trumpington, and there they eate a meſſe of Creame, whither by chaunce came one of the Procters, with whom both <hi>Rowland</hi> and <hi>Audrey</hi> were verie familiar: him they had in and made him as good chéere as ſuch a ſimple alehouſe could afoord, and there in priuate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed to him all their practiſe, deſiring his furtherance in the matter. The Procter promiſed to do what in him lay for the execution of this merrie action: and there amongſt them they laying and confirming the plot, they went all together home to Cambridge, where they paſt away the time pleaſantly til Satterday came: and then according to promiſe was <hi>Marian</hi> there and met with <hi>Awdrey,</hi> who interteined hir with all the courteſie that he could, ſpending the day at the Tauerne whiles night came, and then he caried hir to the houſe appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſuch a <hi>ſubaudi Domus</hi> as was fit for ſuch a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: and there they ſupt. In the meane time <hi>Rowland</hi> had ſent a letter to hir huſband in <hi>Audreies</hi> name, that his wife being not wel was faine to ſtay at hir kinſwo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man all night, and deſired him to come to hir the next morning, and that her father and the reſt of the gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would come with him, for that they ſhould ſée <hi>Row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> taken in bed with a prettie wench. This letter in all haſt was conueied to Cherryhinton to hir huſband, who reading the contentes waxed ſomewhat iealous, becauſe he had ſéene verie familiar courteſies betweene <hi>Awdrey</hi> and his wife, and thought ſchollers were ſlie fellows, and could deuiſe many ſuch Sophiſtications to make a man a cuckold: but hee conceald his ſuſpicion to himſelfe, and ſhewed the letter to his Father in law and the reſt of the Gentlemen, who as they ſorrowed his wife was not well, ſo they were all glad to ſée ſuch a comicall fortune of <hi>Rowland:</hi> hir huſband taking e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie word for his aduantage, ſaid he would be there by
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:10138:28"/> foure of the clocke to ſée <hi>Rowland</hi> taken vp. Thus they all agreed, and were gone by two of the clocke, where we leaue them comming to Cambridge: and againe to <hi>Marian,</hi> who after ſupper ſat vp late, but <hi>Awdrey</hi> fild hir full of Wine till ſhée was almoſt droncke, that ſhée was verie heauie, and deſired to goe to bed, which ſhe did, and was no ſooner laid but ſhe fell a ſléepe, and <hi>Awdrey</hi> ſlipping out, put out the candle and ſent in <hi>Rowland,</hi> and bad him now goe to his miſtres: hée went into the chamber and lockt the dore, and maiſter <hi>Audrey</hi> ſtole out of the howſe and went to his chamber, leauing <hi>Row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> with his paramour, where I thinke more for en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie of the man then for loue of the woman perhaps hée dubde him one of <hi>Paris</hi> prieſthood, howſoeuer it was ſhe deſcried not how it was, but both fell a ſléepe: on the morrow by foure of the clock was <hi>Marians</hi> huſband, hir father and the reſt of the gentlemen at <hi>Peters</hi> hoſtell, where finding the gate open they went to maiſter <hi>Aw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreys</hi> chamber and raiſed him vp, who quickly ſlipping on his cloathes, welcomed them, and went with them to finde out the Proctor, who watching for their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming was already with a doſen maiſters of Art wel ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed walking in the court yard, &amp; preſentlie went his way with them &amp; came to the houſe where <hi>Rowla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</hi> lay: the Proctor knockt and bade open the dore: who is that quoth the good wife? the Proctor quoth he; open y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doore &amp; that quicklie, or I wil beat it down: the good man came ſtumbling downe in his ſhirt, and the good wife was ſo amaſed that ſhee could not remember to tel hir gueſtes. The Proctor came in, and by the direction of <hi>Awdrey</hi> went ſtraight to the Chamber: who be here quoth the Proctor? none ſir quoth he, but a ſtranger and his wife: beat it open with a halbert quoth the Proctor: and with that for haſt <hi>Marians</hi> huſband ran againſt it, &amp; the dore fell downe and hée into the chamber: with that <hi>Rowland</hi> couered hir cloſe, and ſtepping out of the bed in his ſhirt
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:10138:29"/> aſked what they ment. Ah ſyr <hi>Rowland</hi> quoth the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, I am ſorie wee haue diſeaſed you this morne, I thought ful litle to haue found you here, what is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe you lie out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hoſtel to night? Truly ſir quoth he, I was late abroad this night making merrie with my friends, &amp; ſo I was faine to take vp my lodging here. How do you ſyr <hi>Rowland</hi> quoth <hi>Marians</hi> huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp; hir father, I mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel we ſée you not at Cherryhinton. Oh maiſters quoth he, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there is another comedie to play looke for me: but if you reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber I promiſed you a tragedy firſt, when y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is ſtudied, I warrant I wil viſit you. Poore <hi>Maria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi> lying in bed &amp; hearing al this, how ſhe was betrayed and had laid with <hi>Rowland</hi> all night, &amp; how hir father &amp; hir huſband were there preſent, thought ſurely now <hi>Rouland</hi> to the vttermoſt would be reuenged vpon hir, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe fel into a great ſweat for feare. The Proctor that had his leſſon taught him ſaid, wel ſir <hi>Rowland,</hi> had it bene any other but you that had bin taken abroad and in ſuch a ſuſpected houſe, he ſhould haue gone to the Toule booth: but ſince you haue no other company fare wel. <hi>Awdrey</hi> iogd vpon <hi>Maria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> huſband, &amp; as they were ready to go out of doore, tuſh M. Proctor quoth he, but I maruel you examin not who it is that lies with him, it may bee a pretie wench. What? is there one lies with him? I marie is there ſir quoth he, and with that ſtepping to the bed he threw off all the clothes, and there lay his wife in hir ſmocke.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Sante amen quoth Rowland who is here?</l>
                     <l>Haue you ſeene ſuch a chance this yeare?</l>
                     <l>What a woodcocke to come ſo ſoone</l>
                     <l>Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Cherrihinton to Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bridge before noon,</l>
                     <l>And found a Cuckows neſt.</l>
                     <l>Is this maiſters in earneſt or ieſt?</l>
                     <l>That Rowland ſo earlie in a morne</l>
                     <l>Should make a knaue weare a horne.</l>
                     <l>What man be not agaſt?</l>
                     <l>For you cannot call backe that is paſt.</l>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:10138:29"/>
                  <p>At this all the Schollers fell a laughing, and ſyr <hi>Row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> ſate him downe in his ſhirt, and (to make the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vp, that it might be a right blacke <hi>Santus</hi>) while they laught, cried Cuckowe. The Gentleman ſéeing his wife, and the father the daughter, they were in ſuch a maſe, that they ſtoode as men ſenſeleſſe: they fell out a wée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, the Schollers a laughing, the gentlemen a ſighing, and ſtill <hi>Rowland</hi> kept his wench, and cried Cuckowe: at laſt <hi>Rowland</hi> began thus. Why you my Maiſters and friends of <hi>Cherryhinton,</hi> did I not promiſe you a Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedie, and haue I not nowe brought if to paſſe? I hope this Dame, and you all remember my froſty night, and how I was brought out of the trunck: now am I not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenged well? haue I not had my penyworts? Yes Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leine (quoth the gentleman) and firſt the whore ſhall die: and with that drawing out his Rapier, hee woulde haue kild hir: but the Proctor ſtaide him, and ſhée proteſted ſhée knew not how ſhée came there, but thought ſhée had béene at home in hir bedde. Vpon this all the Schollers perſuaded the gentleman that <hi>Rowland</hi> did it by Negro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mancie, and that if ſhée were the honeſteſt woman in the world, Magicke were able to doe as much: <hi>Rowland</hi> for very pitty affirmde it: and ſo they perſwaded him not to wade further in the matter for his owne credit, but to clappe it vp with ſilence. Shée wept and wroong hir hands, and hir father fate and ſhed teares: but at laſt by the perſuaſion of the Proctor and the other Schollers, <hi>Rowland</hi> and hee for all this were made friendes: his wife and he agréed, as a man perſwaded ſhée was ſacke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, and that it was done by Negromancy: and ſo all merrily went to the Tauerne and drunke, they going to the Colledge, and he to <hi>Cherryhinton,</hi> with full reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on neuer more to let his wife come to <hi>Cambridge,</hi> for feare of the Schollers Art Magicke.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>This tale made them all heartily laugh, euery one
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:10138:30"/> commending the policie of the Scholler, that had inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſo good a reuenge. The Cobler he marked all very di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently, and ſwore there was not a more ſound hiſtory for his turne not in all the <hi>Legenda Aurea:</hi> well it made all the Barge merry, and ſéeing they were al in a dump, they cried who is next? marry that am I quoth the ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, and he began to ſettle himſelfe, whome I can beſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe thus.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The deſcription of the Scholler.</head>
               <l>A Man he was of a ſober looke,</l>
               <l>Giuen much vnto his booke:</l>
               <l>For his viſage was all pale,</l>
               <l>And Clarkes tellen this tale,</l>
               <l>That mickle ſtudie makes men leane,</l>
               <l>As well as doth a curſt queane.</l>
               <l>Apollo radiant and ſheene,</l>
               <l>His patterne long had beene:</l>
               <l>For well ſkild was he,</l>
               <l>In verſes and Poetrie.</l>
               <l>In Palmeſtrie he had ſome lore,</l>
               <l>In other Arts mickle more.</l>
               <l>Mickle could he ſay at each ſteuen,</l>
               <l>Of the liberall Arts ſeuen:</l>
               <l>Of the welking and the Axle tree,</l>
               <l>Whereon the heauens turnde me:</l>
               <l>Of Mercurie and Charles waine,</l>
               <l>And of the Beares twaine:</l>
               <l>Caliſto and hir ſonne conueied thither;</l>
               <l>Which to Seamen ſhew the weather:</l>
               <l>When Neptunus with his mace,</l>
               <l>Will make ſmile Amphitrites face.</l>
               <l>Many other matters of Sophiſtrie.</l>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:10138:30"/>
               <l>Could this Clarke in ſecrecie.</l>
               <l>He could alſo ſpeake of loue,</l>
               <l>Of Paphos and of Venus doue.</l>
               <l>And perhaps though he were a Clarke,</l>
               <l>Yet he could skill in the darke</l>
               <l>As well as a man of lay degree,</l>
               <l>To dallie with a wench in priuitie.</l>
               <l>His attire was all blacke,</l>
               <l>But why doe I longer clacke?</l>
               <l>This Clarke gan report,</l>
               <l>His ſtorie in this ſort.</l>
               <div type="tale">
                  <head>The Schollers tale. Conteining the ſundrie miſfortunes that two Sicilian Louers had, and how at the ende their paſſionate ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes came to a pleaſing ſucceſſe.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen the king of <hi>Tuniſe</hi> was beaten out of his kingdome, &amp; ſought to enter againe by force, <hi>Iacomin Pierro,</hi> and <hi>Alexander Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolo,</hi> two Noble men of <hi>Sicilia,</hi> and both of <hi>Palermo,</hi> for the good will they bare to the king, made certaine tall barkes, and with their aide maugre his enemies, placed the king a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine ſafe in his kingdome: which done they returned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to <hi>Palermo.</hi> This <hi>Iacomin Pierro</hi> had a ſonne cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led alſo <hi>Iacomin,</hi> and this <hi>Alexander</hi> had a daughter cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Katherine,</hi> theſe two being neighbours children fell in loue together, inſomuch that <hi>Iacomin</hi> noting the beautie of <hi>Katherine,</hi> ſeeing with his eie hir outward ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie, and hearing with his eares hir inward vertues and perfection, entred with ſuch déepe inſight into hir qualities, that hee reſolued in himſelfe ſhée and none but ſhée ſhould be the goddeſſe of his affections: &amp; of the other ſide, <hi>Katherine</hi> féeding hir eie with the deſired obiect of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:10138:31"/> his perſon, and with delight pleaſing hir eare with the generall fame that ran through all <hi>Sicilia</hi> of his curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, affability, and valor: determined that none but <hi>Iaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min</hi> ſhould enioy the floure of hir beauty. Theſe two lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers being in ſuch a ſympathie of agréeing paſſions, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued a long while with lookes, baſhfull both to diſcouer the eſſence of their loues: yet at laſt <hi>Iacomin</hi> taking hart at graſſe, finding one day fit place and oportunity, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed vnto hir, how euer ſince his yeares coulde enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine any amorous thought, the <hi>Idea</hi> of hir beautie and vertues remained imprinted in his heart ſo déepely, that none but ſhée could ſatiſfie the end of his inceſſant deſire: which was no other, then the honeſt and honorable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of marriage. <hi>Katherine</hi> who was as willing as hee was deſirous, told him that vpon that condition, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer their Parents ſhould agrée, ſhée was ready to bee at his commaund. Thus they wooed and ended, and all in a ſhort ſpace, for that time parting with a kiſſe. This ſwéete conſent of thoughtes, continued a long time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene theſe two Louers, inſomuch that <hi>Iacomin</hi> reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſhortly to breake the matter to his father, to whome he knew the match would bee moſt pleaſing, for that olde <hi>Iacomin</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi> loued together as Brothers. Whiles thus theſe two Louers held their demaunde in ſuſpence, there fell a deadly iarre betwéene the houſe of the <hi>Iacomins</hi> and the family of the <hi>Bartolos:</hi> inſomuch that not onely all <hi>Palemo,</hi> but almoſt all <hi>Sicilia</hi> was in an vproare, for each tooke Armes againſt other, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men of great Parentage, friendes tooke partes, and they began to bandy, that they fell to a flatte ciuill diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſention. This diſagreement betweene the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, although it was a heart breake to the two Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, yet could it not at all diſparage their affection, but the greater the Mutinie the deeper was the impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of their mindes. But by this meanes their mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting was hindered: yet Loue being a priuie ſearcher of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:10138:31"/> ſecrets, found them out a creuiſe betwéene two walles, which parted their houſes, and there oft times they met and parled, hoping ſtil ſome end would grow to this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall diſſention: but as the fier increaſeth with the wind, ſo this iar grew greater by time, that the louers loſt all hope euer to haue conſent of parents: inſomuch, that wholy in diſpaire of an vnitie, they concluded to forſake <hi>Sicilia,</hi> and to goe into <hi>Spaine,</hi> where they had both friends, and there to remaine til their families were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded. Vpon this reſolution, <hi>Iacomine</hi> prouides him a Barke, and laide it readie in the hauen, and when the winde and weather was faire, gaue a watchword to <hi>Katherine,</hi> and ſo got hir a boord, hoiſt ſailes and away they made towards <hi>Spaine:</hi> they were not long gon, but they were miſt, and by all poſſible coniectures knowne to be ſlipt away together, for diuers manifeſt inſtancies were reported of their loues. The fathers fell both into déepe paſſions, <hi>Iacomyn</hi> hauing but one Sonne, and <hi>Bartolo</hi> but one Daughter: yea the gréefe of their vnkind departure, did ſo worke in their Fathers mindes, that each intended more miſchéefe to other, as it were in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge, that the broils grew hotter. But as they diſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted, ſo theſe two Louers accorded euery way, looking for no other Hauen but the coaſt of <hi>Spaine:</hi> but fortune that delights to ſport hir ſelfe in the variable accidents of loue, brought it thus to paſſe. They had not ſailde thrée daies from <hi>Sicilia,</hi> but that there fell a great calme, and certaine Gallies that were Rouers vnder the king of <hi>Tmiſa,</hi> eſpied this <hi>Sicilian</hi> ſhip: and thinking to haue ſome rich priſe, made out and gaue onſet, commaunding them to yéeld: the <hi>Sicilians,</hi> being calme, could not make way from them, but yet although too weake, ſtoutly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied to be bourded, and fought it out to the vttermoſt, chéefelie <hi>Iacomine,</hi> who was ſore wounded: but at laſt, they of the Gallies entered, and beſtowed the Mariners vnder hatches, and then went to rifle the Ship, where
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:10138:32"/> they found <hi>Katherine</hi> al blubbered with teares, &amp; almoſt dead for feare, hir they tooke for all hir pittifull ſhrikes and cries, conueyed hir into the Gallies: which <hi>Iacomin</hi> ſéeing, tooke ſo heauily, that hee was readie to die for gréefe: but ſo ſore he was hurt, that ſtir he could not, but was faine to ſuffer hir to be carried away, whether the mercie of the ſlaues pleaſed to tranſport hir: when they had rifeled the ſhip, and found nothing but paſſengers, away they we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with faire <hi>Katherine,</hi> determining with themſelues to giue hir for a preſent to the king of <hi>Tuniſe</hi> whom they knew did loue a faire woman, more then halfe his kingdome, and ſo faire a creature as <hi>Katherine</hi> they were ſure he neuer ſaw before. Vpon this they made ſaile towards <hi>Tuniſe,</hi> and when they were arriued, the captaine of the Gallies, cauſing hir to dreſſe hir in hir richeſt attire, we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with hir to the Kings Palace, where when he was admitted to his Highneſſe preſence, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly on his knées he craued pardon, as one that contrarie to his Maieſties lawes had bin a Rouer and a Pirate on the ſeas: but now loathing that courſe of life, was come to ſubmit himſelfe, &amp; hauing taken that Gentlewoman as a priſe at ſea, deſired his Maieſtie to accept hir as a preſent. The king whiles the Pirate told his tale, kept his eye ſtill on the Gentlewoman, whoſe beautie he fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſuch, that he thought her ſome heauenly creature, ſhrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in ſome mortall carcaſſe. The king not only thanked the Pirat for his preſent, but gaue him frée pardon, and a letter of mart, with many other rich gifts, ſo that he returned richly rewarded: and then turning him to <hi>Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therine,</hi> he tooke hir in his armes, kiſt her, and gaue hir ſuch enterteinement as in all roialtie he could. But no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could make hir ceaſe off from teares, hauing ſtill hir <hi>Iacomin</hi> in remembrance, whom ſhe held for dead: which the King perceiuing, commaunded that ſhe ſhould be carried to a place of his, ſtanding faſt by the Cittie wall, and there placed and attended vpon with all dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:10138:32"/> vntill ſhe might be comforted, and thither when it pleaſed him hee would haue recourſe. Seated in that houſe, there ſhe led a ſolitarie life, waſhing hir chéekes euery day with teares for hir poore <hi>Iacomin:</hi> who like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe wounded as he was, was brought to <hi>Tuniſe,</hi> and there left in the Surgions hand, where he was healed: aſſoone as he might well goe, he went as a man forlorne vp and downe the Cittie, looking euery where if hee might ſée his <hi>Katherine:</hi> wherevpon he reſolued to paſſe from place to place, and ſo to end his daies in trauell, if he did not by narrow inquiſition finde hir out: getting therefore his bag and baggage in a readineſſe, he was going out of <hi>Tuniſe;</hi> and as he paſſing out the gates, caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his eie vp to the houſe where <hi>Katherine</hi> was, who at that time was looking out of a caſement, hee eſpied her, and thinking it ſhould be ſhe, ſtood in a maſe: <hi>Katherine</hi> ſéeing him, and thinking him to be her <hi>Iacomin,</hi> was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ready to fall downe in a ſounde: thus ſtood the two Louers at gaſe; at laſt <hi>Iacomin</hi> cald <hi>Katherine: Iaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min</hi> (quoth ſhe) and with that ſhe clapt hir finger on hir mouth, and made a ſigne, that for that time he ſhould depart. Backe againe went <hi>Iacomin</hi> to his Hoſteſſe, as merry a man as might be, &amp; there ſtaid till it was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing late in the euening, and then going to the place, ſought round about the houſe, and there found a backe window into a Garden, where they might conueniently talke: he had not ſtayed there long, but <hi>Katherine</hi> came to the window, and there after a volly of ſighes, quencht with teares, they began to diſcourſe their fortunes ſince their departure: <hi>Katherine</hi> told <hi>Iacomin</hi> how ſhe was giuen by the Pirates to the King for a preſent, and how he had placſt hir there, reſeruing hir for one of his Concubines, and that ſhee looked euery hower, when he ſhould come to defloure hir. Therefore quoth ſhe, ſince wee are man and wife, as wee haue liued to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, ſo let vs dye together, and enioye thou the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:10138:33"/> chaſtitie of that body, whoſe ſoule hath béene euer thine in all amitie: I reſpect not the King, nor what his tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures can doo, therefore at night come hither to this place when it is darke, climbe vp on the wall, and ſo on this trée, and thou maiſt eaſilie come into the caſement, which for the ſame purpoſe thou ſhalt find open. At this motion <hi>Iacomin</hi> was glad, and ſo departed, and at the time appointed came: and being made more nimble by loue and deſire, he lept vp the wall lightly, and ſo into the trée, and from thence into the caſement, where hee found his <hi>Katherine</hi> ready to receiue him, banquet him ſhe could not, leaſt any might heare, but feaſt he did with kiſſes, or whatſoeuer ſhe might affoord to his amorous deſires, ſo that in the end, to bed they went, and there with pleaſure recompenſed their former miſfortunes. Loue hauing thus aduanced hir champion; Fortune enuying their happineſſe, ment to haue one fling more at them, and brought it ſo to paſſe, that the King that night reſolued to haue the companie of <hi>Katherine,</hi> and therefore after all his Lordes were at reſt, tooke with him his Chamberlaine, and certaine of his Garde, and went to his place where ſhe lay, comming in by a backe gate, hauing keyes for euery doore, at laſt opened the Chamber where ſhe was, and there drawing the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens to behold his Goddeſſe, he ſaw where ſhe lay with a yoongman in hir armes faſt a ſléepe: the king for anger was ready to haue kild them, but yet he did qualifie his furie with a royall patience: and called his Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine, and the reſt of his Garde, and ſhewed them this ſight, demanding of them if any of them knew the yong man: they all anſwered, no, but ſuppoſed he was ſome ſtranger. The King ſtraight commaunded, that certaine of his Garde ſhould watch them, and aſſoone as they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakt, carry them to priſon, and let there in the midſt of the market place be erected a great ſtake, and in the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne one, there let them be both conſumed with fier: the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:10138:33"/> gard obeied the Kings commaundement, &amp; hee went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way in great choller, and highlie diſcontented. The King departed, theſe louers ſlept ſwéetelie till the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and then they awooke, where preſent they heard a ruſtling of men, who ſtraight tould them how y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> King was there, what had hapned, and what hee had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded: therefore they made them riſe, &amp; then bound them and carried them away. The two louers were no whit diſmaied at this newes, but imbracing &amp; kiſſing each other, comforted themſelues in this, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhould, as they liued together ſo die together, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their ſoules nor bodies ſhould neuer part. Straight were they ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to priſon, &amp; the ſtake was on prouiding, wherupon the rumour of their burning came about the cittie, that againſt the hower appointed all the cittie were gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red together, and forth at laſt was <hi>Iacomine</hi> and <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therin</hi> brought, and bound to the ſtake backe to backe: They earneſtlie deſired y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they might be bound face to face, but it could not be granted, which gréeued the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forted themſelues with chéerful woords, reſolued to ſuffer death with patience. Al the cittie was gathered together, &amp; ſtood gaſing on them, &amp; pittying them, that ſo ſwéete a couple ſhould fall in ſuch fatal extremitie: the poore ſoules aſhamed, and hanging downe their heads expecting euerie minute the beginning of their martir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: As thus the fire was readie to be brought came the Lord high Admirall of <hi>Tunyſe</hi> bye, and ſeeing ſuch a concourſe, demaunded the cauſe: The people tould him as much as they knew. He on his footcloth came to the ſtake, and looking vpon them ſéeing them ſo louely, aſked of them of what Countrey they were. Of Sycilia ſir quoth <hi>Iacomine.</hi> With that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Admiral ſtaring him ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtlie in the face called to his remembrance the fauour of old <hi>Iacomine</hi> his father. Of what place in Sicilia? my friend quoth he: of Palermo: thy name quoth the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral: <hi>Iacomin</hi> quoth he: why thou art not (anſwered the Lord) the ſonne of <hi>Iacomin Pierro?</hi> yes quoth he, and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:10138:34"/> this the daughter of <hi>Alexander Bartolo:</hi> And if quoth <hi>Iacomine</hi> you knew thoſe families, do but ſo much for vs as ſpeake to the king, that wee may be bound face to face, &amp; ſo die, for life that we hold in ſkorne. Although the torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tors were appointed to diſpatch the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by an hower, yet the L. Admirall chargd them not to put any fire to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wood til his return; which they promiſd: &amp; away gallops y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Admiral as a mad man through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtreetes to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Kings palace, where when he came, he found y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king in a great rage, diſcourſing to his Lords the villany of <hi>Catherin,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> admitted a ſtranger into her. The Admiral without any great reuerence, as a man ful of choller began thus roughlie and brieflie. Can they which place kinges pull down kings? Then looke thou once againe to be beaten out of <hi>Tunyſe:</hi> did <hi>Iacomine Pierro</hi> &amp; <hi>Alexander Bartolo</hi> the two valia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Lords of Sicilia by their force ſeat thée in thy kingdome? and now in reuenge doſt thou burne the onelie iſſue of them both? for that two louers ſeeke the fruition of their loues, ſo ſhal wee haue Sicilia our enemies, and thou ſéeke a new kingdome. What mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt thou to vſe theſe railing ſpéeches quoth the King? Marie quoth the Admiral, yonder yong gentleman that is at the ſtake is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſon of <hi>Iacomin,</hi> &amp; ſhe the daughter of <hi>Bartolo.</hi> At this the king ſtood in amaze, &amp; was halfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid, ſo that he cryed out to his Lords, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhould ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; bring the couple as they were to him: which they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed with all diligence. When <hi>Iacomine</hi> and <hi>Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rin</hi> ſaw the nobles come, then they lookt for the fire: but when they heard how they muſt bee vnlooſed, and how curteouſlie they were intreated, hope of better fortune gaue them ſome comfort. Well, away they were caried to the king, who graciouſlie interteining them, demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the cauſe of their bould enterpriſe, and what for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune brought them into ſuch a far countrey. <hi>Iacomine</hi> ſtraight began and diſcourſt their particular hap, and what accident <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> they had, whoſe ſonnes they were, and what was their contrarie fortunes. The king at this
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:10138:34"/> embracſt them both, welcomd them, and craued pardon of his raſh cenſure, cladding them in roial apparel, and inryching them with manie coſtlie giftes, after ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemplie married them in <hi>Tuniſe,</hi> and kept a great feaſt with turney and triumphes fitting their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, and after preparing a prettie Fleet, ſent them home to their parentes by the Lord Admiral: whoſe arriual in Palermo was wonderful ſtrange, in that all thought they were dead. But when they recounted to their parents their miſfortunes, and laſt the gracious fauoures of the King of <hi>Tuniſe,</hi> by the helpe and good perſwaſion of the Lord Admirall; the inſtance of their true loue reconciled their fathers and families, that not onelie the two louers agréed, but the two houſes euer after continued in peace and concord.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>Aſſoone as the ſcholler had tould his tale, euerie man thanckt him for his paines, and ſaid it was a pleaſant and a delightfull hiſtorie: amongeſt the reſt there was an old woman, who for verie kindneſſe to heare of their hard haps, and the good fortunes of the louers, wept: why weepe you mother quoth the Cobler? by my troth ſonne quoth ſhee, to thinke on the chaunces of loue which are ſo variable, &amp; by the grace of God if all in the barge will giue mee leaue, you ſhal heare an old woman tell a tale that will make you all merie. Euerie man deſired hir to ſay on: and ſhe béeing a ſimple woman, as you ſhal perceiue by hir deſcription, ſetled hir ſelfe to hir taſke thus.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The deſcription of the old Woman.</head>
               <l>CRooked was this beldam for age,</l>
               <l>Huffe ſhouldred, and of a wrinckled viſage:</l>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:10138:35"/>
               <l>And as hir backe and necke was croked,</l>
               <l>So was hir noſe long and hooked.</l>
               <l>Manie forrowes in hir brow,</l>
               <l>Hairy, and briſtled like a Sow.</l>
               <l>Shee had a large tawny face,</l>
               <l>And therein an il fauored grace.</l>
               <l>Shee was mouthed like a Sparrow,</l>
               <l>Gated like a wheelebarow,</l>
               <l>And of long time beforne</l>
               <l>Not a tooth in hir head had ſhe borne.</l>
               <l>Yet could ſhe chew good ale,</l>
               <l>For her noſe was nothing pale,</l>
               <l>But with ſwinking at hir will</l>
               <l>Shee lookt red about the gill.</l>
               <l>Mickle talke ſhe had and mickle chat</l>
               <l>When with hir Goſſips ſhe ſat,</l>
               <l>That threeſcore yeares before</l>
               <l>The bell for goſſipping ſhe bore.</l>
               <l>Hir apparell was after the elder bere.</l>
               <l>Hir caſſocke aged ſome fiftie yere:</l>
               <l>Graie it was, and long beforne</l>
               <l>The wool from the threedes was worne.</l>
               <l>A thrumbe hat ſhe had of red</l>
               <l>Like a buſhel on her head.</l>
               <l>Hir kercher hung from vnder her cap</l>
               <l>With a taile like a flie flap,</l>
               <l>And tied it was with a whim wham,</l>
               <l>Knit vp againe with a trim tram,</l>
               <l>Much like an Egiptian.</l>
               <l>Hir ſleeues blew, hir traine behind</l>
               <l>With ſiluer hookes was tucked I find.</l>
               <l>Hir ſhooes broad and forked before,</l>
               <l>None ſuch ſaw I of yore.</l>
               <l>This beldam on hir merrie pin</l>
               <l>Began hir tale with this gin.</l>
               <div type="tale">
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:10138:35"/>
                  <head>The old wiues tale, Conteining the wilie ſleightes of a wanton wife, and how both cunninglie and craftilie to the ſafety of her owne honeſtie and hir huſbandes diſcredite, ſhee ſhifted hir louer.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N a farre countrey there dwelled ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time a gentleman of good pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage, called ſignior <hi>Myzaldo,</hi> who had to his wife a verie faire and beautifull gentlewoman. And as the beaſtes moſt gréedilie gaſe at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Panthers ſkin, &amp; the birdes at the Peacocks plumes: ſo euery fair feminine face is an adamant to draw y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> obiect of mens eies to behold the beauties of women: experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence prooued it true in the wife of <hi>Myzaldo,</hi> for ſhe being a woman of ſingular perfection and proportion, was generallie looked on and liked of al, but fauoured and loued eſpeciallie of a yong gentleman called <hi>Peter,</hi> dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with ſuch ſecrecie, that they continuallie ſatiſfied their deſires without giuing ſignior <hi>Myzaldo</hi> the leaſt occaſion of ſuſpition; and the meanes that they perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it with ſuch ſecrecie was this. Euerie wéeke twiſe hir huſband rid from home about certaine his affaires, and ſhe very artificially néere to the high way that leads to the towne where <hi>Peter</hi> lay, had placed an aſſes head vpon a tree, and when hir huſband was gone forth, ſhe tourned y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> head towards the town; but when he was at home, then ſhe alwaies had it looking to hir own houſe: vſing herein as ſome thought, an Embleame, ſaying, when ſhe turnd the Aſſes head forth, that the Aſſe hir huſbande with the long horning eares was gone from home; and when it ſtood towards the howſe, that the Aſſe kept his chamber: but what ſoeuer in this hir conceit was, <hi>Peter</hi> alwaies knew when to come, and euer when <hi>Myzaldo</hi> was from home reſorted to his houſe. Now it chanced that certaine boyes comming by and ſéeing the Aſſes head ſtand there, threw ſtones
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:10138:36"/> at it, &amp; hit it ſo often, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> at laſt they turned the Aſſes head towards y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> town: which <hi>Peter</hi> walking abroad &amp; ſpying, thought y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>Myzaldo</hi> had bin gone from home: &amp; therfore at night walked towards his louers houſe, &amp; comming to the dore finding it ſhut, according to his accuſtomed maner, knockt: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good wife awakt, heard him &amp; was ſore afraid y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hir huſband ſhould heare him, and ſo lay ſtill: by and by he knockt again mor lowd: <hi>Myzaldo</hi> awoke, &amp; hearing this, aſked of his wife who it was that rapt at the doore, or what y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> knocking meant? Oh huſband quoth ſhe, be ſtil, it is a foule ſpirit y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hauntes this houſe, &amp; yet hetherto we neuer durſt reueale it, and it hath, thanks be to God, bin your good fortune neuer to hear it before: <hi>Myzaldo</hi> rycher by far then he was wiſe, beléeued his wife, &amp; aſkt hir if it had done any harme: no quoth ſhee, for I had learnd a charm to ſend it hence: frier <hi>Rowla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</hi> learnd me it, and if it knocke againe, you and I wil goe down together, &amp; I wil ſay my charme, &amp; ſo we ſhal liue at reſt. <hi>Peter</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thought ſom other frend had bin with his Le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man, taking it in ſcorn y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hir huſband (as he thought) being fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> home he ſhould not be let in, knockt againe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine. With y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>Myzaldo</hi> &amp; his wife aroſe, lighted a can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, &amp; went downe to the dore where <hi>Peter</hi> was: Then ſhe wiſht hir huſband to knéele downe vpon his knées while ſhe ſaid the charme. With that ſhe began thus.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Spirit ſpirit get thee hence,</l>
                     <l>For here is no reſidence:</l>
                     <l>Here thou maiſt not be</l>
                     <l>This night to trouble me,</l>
                     <l>For my huſband and I</l>
                     <l>Safe in our beds muſt lie,</l>
                     <l>Therfore from hence goe</l>
                     <l>And trouble me no mo.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Now huſband quoth ſhe, ſpit: &amp; with that he ſpit, and <hi>Peter</hi> laught hartily, and wiſht he might ſpit out his teeth for being at home. This charme ſaid ſhee thriſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:10138:36"/> and euery time made him ſpit, that <hi>Peter</hi> might be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly perſwaded that hir huſband was at home. Vpon this <hi>Myzaldo</hi> and his wife went to bed, and heard the ſpirit no more: for <hi>Peter</hi> we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t laughing home to his lodging. <hi>Myzaldo</hi> could not ſléepe this night, nor many nights after, but ſtill maruelling what this ſpirit ſhould be, lay a woke. <hi>Peter</hi> that once or twiſe thus was deceiued of the aſſe head, becauſe by ſom co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary miſhap it was turnd, deuiſed thus: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euery night when <hi>Myzaldos</hi> wife we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to bed ſhe ſhould tie a ſtring to hir toe, &amp; then leaue the ende of it at the dore, ſo that when <hi>Peter</hi> came he might wake hir, &amp; then if ſhe puld the ſtring againe &amp; tied it faſt, hir huſband was from home: if ſhe let it ſlip, then he was in bed. Thus by the means of this ſtring <hi>Myzaldo</hi> was oft made cuckold, and ſometimes when hir huſband was at home &amp; in his ſound ſléepe, if <hi>Peter</hi> puld the ſtring, ſhe would riſe &amp; go down to him to the dore. At laſt ſo thus this game continued, that <hi>Myzaldos</hi> wife being faſt a ſléepe, and he riſing to find y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chamber pot ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtring, and wondring what it ment, or to what end groped eaſilie &amp; found it tied to his wiues toe, and from thence reacht to the dore. He, as ſimple as he was, coniectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that this was done to make him cuckold, and therefore for that night ſaid nothing: but againſt the next night had prouided a great Partiſan by his beds ſide: and when his wife was faſt a ſléepe he vntied the ſtring, and ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it to his owne toe; hee had not ſtumbred a little, but hee felt the ſtring pull eaſilie, whereupon hee puld againe, and then <hi>Peter</hi> thought aſſuredlie that hee was gone from home, whereupon he knockt. Then did <hi>Myzaldo</hi> riſe, put on his cloathes, and tooke the partizan in his hand, and downe hee went ruſtling that his wife wakt, and hearing him go down ſo haſtilie felt for the ſtring that was at hir toe, &amp; miſt it: wherupon ſhe perceiued hir huſband had found out the deceipt, and whipping out of the bed ran down the ſtaires: with that <hi>Mizaldo</hi> opened the dore and thought to haue taken <hi>Peter,</hi> but hee hauing a glaunce of him being in a dark night came away, &amp; <hi>Mizaldo</hi> after him, and raiſed
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:10138:37"/> the watch, yet was <hi>Peter</hi> ſo light of foot, that he out ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them al, &amp; eſcapt. <hi>Mizaldoes</hi> wife fearing the worſt ran vp againe to hir maid, &amp; wild hir to goe to hir bed, and lie there, &amp; to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide whatſoeuer hir huſband ſhould do to hir, &amp; ſhee would giue hir a new gowne &amp; a new petticote. The wench was content and went to her maiſters bed: ſcarſe was ſhe warm there, but vp came <hi>Mizaldo</hi> in a great rage, &amp; ſtraight lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down his partizan fel to beating of his wife, and with a whipcord all to laſht hir bodie, that the blood ran downe the ſhéetes: and when he had done, in the darke groped, &amp; found a paire of ſhears &amp; clipt off all the haire of hir head: and that done, opened the dore and went his way. The wench almoſt kild with blowes, and ſore pained with ſmart lay ſtil as one in a traunce: but aſſoon as euer <hi>Mizaldo</hi> was gone, his wife aroſe and ſhut the dore, and came to the wench, where ſhee comforted and waſht hir, &amp; annointed her, putting on cleane linnen vpon hir, &amp; laid cleane ſhéetes on the bed, and ſo ſate downe diſcontented at hir work. No ſooner did the day break but ſignior <hi>Mizaldo</hi> went with all ſpéed to his mother in lawe, and there reuealed to hir and to his wiues brethren how his wife had delt with him, and how he had reuenged hir, yet not ſufficientlie, but was fullie reſolued to bring hir this day before the Magiſtrate, &amp; ſo abſolutely to make a diuorce: the mother fel to wéeping, and knowing hir own fault when ſhee was young, intreated hir ſonnes that they would make a peace &amp; attoneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t betwéeene their ſiſter and hir huſband: they fell to exclaime againſt hir, and ſaid, ſéeing ſhe was by hir lightnes the diſcredit of hir houſe, they would be the firſt and the formoſt in puniſhing ſuch groſſe offences. Vpon this they went home with <hi>Myzaldo</hi> to his houſe, and there comming vp the ſtaires they found their daughter ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting verie ſad: the huſband fround and bretheren ſcoulded, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mother whom nature more néerely toucht, ſaid, what chéere daughter? what ſtir is this betwéene your huſband &amp; you? what ſtir quoth hir daughter? marrie I would you &amp; my brethren had gone to my burying whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you went to my mariage to wed mee to a dronckard, that all day goes out
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:10138:37"/> about whores and curtiſans, and at night comes home late, and perhaps not all night, as he hath doone now, and ſo doo I ſit all day comfortleſſe, and lie in the night like a widow while he is abroad with his ſtrumpets. And quoth the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he is this morning come to your brethren and me, with an outcrie againſt you, that this night he tooke you with a Lemman at the doore, and how he found it out by a ſtring tied to your toe. Fie vpon him dronkard (quoth ſhe) theſe are his dreames, when he lies tipled in the Tauerne: but I maruell where he hath béene to night: marry Dame quoth he, I feare me your fleſh and your bones knowe too well, for I thinke you haue not one frée ſpot on your body, I ſo whipt you for your whoredome, and I thinke the ſhéetes in the bed can witneſſe, and the haire that I cut off your head can teſtifie. Now mother (quoth ſhe) and good brethren, ſée whether this is an arrand droonkard or not, that tels theſe fables, ſaying, he beat me thus to night, when he toucht me not, nor before this time ſince yeſterday morning, came within theſe doores: where he ſaies the ſhéetes are bloudie, ſée brethren ſée, they are cleane: for my ſkin, take view of it, if it be any way toucht: and for my haire, ſée how faire and long it is: how hath he then done theſe prankes? alas, alas, he hath falne amongſt his whores in his droonkenneſſe, and hath vſed them ſo, and now to the ſlander of me, to the diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of my fréends, and the perpetuall infamie of our houſe, he hath thus without cauſe reuiled me, where yée ſée his owne lying toong condemnes him. <hi>Mizaldo,</hi> ſéeing neither his wiues haire cut, nor hir bodie any way bruſed, fell into a great dumpe, woondering whether he drempt it or no, in ſo much, that at laſt he aſkt: whie Wife? was I not this night at home? at home, in faith ſir no, but with ſome of your brabs, &amp; I thinke thou cameſt home dronke. At this doubtful demaund, hir brethren began to take hir part, &amp; ſeeing what he ſaid was falſe, &amp; al hir ſpéeches probable, they raild on him in moſt bitter termes, &amp; told him in that he had maried their ſiſter who was an honeſt woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; he by all means ſought to depriue hir of hir good name without cauſe, who ſhould be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:10138:38"/> protector of hir honor, they would not put it vp vnreuenged, but would to the vttermoſt do him what iniurie the extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie of the law would affoord. Vpon this, the man ſéeing how in all things his wife had diſprooued him, thought aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly that he was not at home the laſt night, and therfore deſired hir to pardon him, and he would neuer after be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the like offence, and ſo vpon that, by hir mother and hir brethren they were made friends, and euer after <hi>Peter</hi> and ſhe with leſſe ſuſpition enioyed their loues.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>The old wife hauing tould hir tale, euery man began to commend the wit of a woman, who on the ſudden is euer moſt quick, &amp; percing, able ſo ſoone to yéeld a peremptorie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, as the occaſion is miniſtred. By that they had told this tale, they were within ſight of Graueſend: wherevpon they thought to haue giuen ouer, but that a Somner ſat by, who was a pleaſant fellow; and he began thus. Gentlemen ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the motion of the Cobler, we haue imitated ould Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Chaucer,</hi> hauing in our little Barge, as he had in his trauell ſundry tales, and amongſt the reſt, the old wiues tale, that you ſhall not want the merrieſt knaue of all the Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, you ſhall heare what I can ſay; and to kéepe <hi>decorum,</hi> as the Cobler began with the tale of a Prior, I will end with one of an Abbot: they all thankt him heartily, and he began thus. But firſt I muſt, as hitherto I haue doone all, deſcribe him.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The deſcription of the Somner.</head>
               <l>THis Somner was not very old,</l>
               <l>Of a countenance ſtout and bold:</l>
               <l>That would againſt the truth wage,</l>
               <l>For he had a ſhameleſſe viſage.</l>
               <l>Squint eyed he was, and his head</l>
               <l>Was bad hued, bloud red:</l>
               <l>A noſe he had that gan ſhow,</l>
               <l>What liquor he loued I trow.</l>
               <l>For he had before long ſeauen yeare,</l>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:10138:38"/>
               <l>Beene of the towne the Ale conner.</l>
               <l>His face was full of pretious ſtone,</l>
               <l>Richer in Inde was neuer none:</l>
               <l>For Rubie, Pearle, and Chryſolite,</l>
               <l>With them all his face was dight</l>
               <l>From the brow to the very chin,</l>
               <l>Yet to drinke he would neare lin:</l>
               <l>But ſwincked with all his might,</l>
               <l>At euery houſe where he did ſite.</l>
               <l>His conditions were faire and good,</l>
               <l>For why he was by the roode</l>
               <l>Acquainted with rich and eke with poore,</l>
               <l>And kend well euery kerne whore,</l>
               <l>Or other wife that held no ſcorne</l>
               <l>To make hir huſband were the horne.</l>
               <l>Such a knaue he was indeed,</l>
               <l>That as true as my creede,</l>
               <l>He cited euery woman to the law,</l>
               <l>Euen for the valew of a ſtraw.</l>
               <l>And ſommon them to appeare</l>
               <l>At the bawdy court as I leere:</l>
               <l>Where for money the Somner</l>
               <l>Would all their faults cleere:</l>
               <l>That they ſhould not appeare at all,</l>
               <l>Before the officiall.</l>
               <l>A Bawd he was, a teltale, and a knaue,</l>
               <l>Sike an other it is ſeld to haue,</l>
               <l>Vnleſſe a man ſhould hell rake,</l>
               <l>There to finde out his make.</l>
               <l>Yet gan he thus declare,</l>
               <l>How the Abbot of Wickam did fare.</l>
               <div type="tale">
                  <head>¶The Somners tale, Conteining the ſhifts that the Abbot made to haue his loue, and how he raiſd a man from death.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N <hi>Wickham</hi> there was an Abbot, that was a man of a middle age, luſtie and frolike, and coueted to
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:10138:39"/> acquaint himſelfe with all the faire Wiues of the Towne, inſomuch that euery man doubted of this iolly Clarke: yet he made himſelfe holy, but doo what he could, it might not cléere the ſuſpition that the men of the towne had of him: Amongſt the reſt, hee was acquainted with a Farmars Wife, that was none of the wiſeſt, and yet he had witte e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to beware of the Abbot. This Farmar excéeded all the reſt, not onely of the Towne, but of all the whole coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie about for iealouſie, being ſo ſuſpitious of his Wife, that he would brooke none of his neighbours to come into his houſe, and if ſhe glauncſt hir lookes neuer ſo little awry, he would ſtraight beate hir while he could ſtand ouer hir, in ſo much, that the woman was wearie of hir life, and looked as a creature forlorne.</p>
                  <p>As ſhée was one daye walking into the fields to doe hir buſineſſe, the Abbot met hir, who tooke hir by the hand, and began to make loue to hir: ſhe was both coie and fearefull: yet at laſt the Abbot gan ſo prattle, that ſhee began to tell him how iealous hir huſband was, and how wearie ſhée was of hir life. Tuſhe (quoth the Abbot) care not for that, referre that matter to mee, I will ſtraight cure him of his iealouſie, if then thou wilt bee my paramour. So ſore was the poore woman troubled with a iealous foole, that ſhee was glad to graunt whatſoeuer the Abbot would aſke, ſo hir huſband might bee mended of his fault: make ſome excuſe quoth the Abbot, ſend him to me to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and then let me alone: but whatſoeuer thou heareſt is befallen him, feare not, all ſhall be well. Vpon that the Farmars Wife and the Abbot parted, ſhee to hir houſe, he to his cloiſter, where hee called one of his Monkes, in whome he did repoſe all his truſt, and reuealed vnto him the whole matter, and what plot hee had laid to bring his purpoſe to paſſe: the Moonke condiſcended to doe what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer the Abbot ſhould commaund, and ſo vpon this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution they laught, and the next day came the Farmar to the Abbot to haue a hie maſſe ſaid for one of his Children that was ſick: the Abbot made much of him, and bad him to
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:10138:39"/> dinner, and ſubtilly at his laſt draught conueied a dormatiue potion into the cup, that preſently after dinner he fell into a dead ſléepe; that his ſenſes being gone all men thought he was deade: wherefore preſently one of the Monkes ran to the good wife, and tolde hir what had happened to hir huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band: ſhée cried out and wrung hir hands, and tolde it to hir neighbours: whereupon ſhée and a great company both of men and women went to the Abbey, and there was hee knit vp in his winding ſhéete, the wife pittifully lamented, and the neighbours comforted hir: the Abbot he ſaide he ſhould be buried in their Abbey becauſe he died there, and therefore in preſence of them all ſolemnely buried him: which done, his wife like a ſorrowfull woman departed home to hir houſe with hir neighbours.</p>
                  <p>Aſſoone as night came, the Abbot and the Monke, (whom hee had made priuy to this practiſe) went and cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly tooke him out of his graue, and carried him into a déepe dungeon, where he could ſée no light, and there let him lie ſtarke naked, till ſuch time as the potion had ended the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration, and that hee ſhould wake. At length the Farmar a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woke, and ſtretching himſelfe, finding that he was naked, and in a place lothſome, darke, and fearefull, he could not tel what to thinke, but bleſt himſelfe, and ſaid, Lord haue mercie vpon me, where am I? The Monke that was by attired like a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, ſaide, thou art deade and in purgatory. Deade quoth the Farmer: can dead men ſpeak? Yea quoth the Monke, and eat too, ſuch meate and drinke as is appointed for the dead: This day in the morning thou didſt die, and thy wife did bury thée in the Abbey, accompanied with all hir neighbours: and I wretch a ſpirite of purgatorie, am appointed to torment thée without ceaſing, for that in thy life time thou wert iealous, and didſt miſuſe thy wife without cauſe, therefore am I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to vexe thée thréeſcore and tenne yeares without cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing: and with that hauing a whippe in his hande, the Monke laide it on, and gaue him many a ſhrewde blowe: At laſt he left him and went his way, and told the Abbot what he had done.</p>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:10138:40"/>
                  <p>The Abbot as ſoone as conuenient leyſure woulde ſerue, ſtole ſecretly to the Farmers houſe, and there got to bed to the goodwife, and euery night lay with hir while hir huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band was in purgatorie: and euery day the Monke went down and allowed him a little pittance of meat and drinke: but whipt him moſt miſerably. At laſt the Farmer grew to be maruellous penitent and repentant for his faults, ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that if he were aliue againe, he would neuer be iealous nor ſuſpitious: earneſtly praying his wife that ſhée woulde forgiue him. While thus the poore Farmer was in his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory almoſt whipt to death, and famiſht, the Abbot and his wife liued in all pleaſure and iolity, laughing when they heard the Monke report what the poore man ſaid in his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory: At laſt ſhée perceiued that ſhée was with child, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they muſt néeds haue a father for it, wherupon they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed to haue him out of purgatorie, and to bring him home with a miracle. The next day the Monke came to him accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his accuſtomed manner, and whipt him not, but told him that his wife euery day offred a Taper for him, and ſaid ſo many good praiers, that his ſinnes were remitted, and his puniſhment forgiuen: whereupon hee thankt his wife and made a vow, if God ſhould reſtore him to life (as it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible) he would not onely leaue to be iealous himſelfe, but warne all other men to take héede of the like fault. Thus continued hee without whipping by the ſpace of fiue or ſixe daies, and at laſt the Monke in ſtead of drinke, gaue him an other dormatiue potion, ſo that he fell a ſléepe.</p>
                  <p>Then the Abbot and the Monke in the night conueied him into the place where hee was buried, and ſo let him lie. About the houre when hee knewe hee would wake, was the Monke there, faining himſelfe at praier: and aſſoone as euer he ſaw him ſtir, he ranne away and cried out: vpon this all the Monkes of the Cloiſter roſe, and aſkt what the matter was. Oh quoth hee, as I was in praier by the Farmers graue, I heard a tumbling and a voice there either of him or of a ſpirite? with that the Monkes went downe and found that there was one aliue within the Tombe: then they
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:10138:40" rendition="simple:additions"/> called the Abbot and tolde him, who ſlipping on his night gowne, ran apace to ſee the miracle: when he came there, and they were all gathered together, they lifted vp the ſtone, and there lay he tumbling in his ſhéete: ſo they tooke him out and vndid him, and he looked wan and gaſh, but ſpake to them and tolde them, that the Lorde at the praiers of his wife had reſtored him to life, and that hee had béene in purgatory, and what puniſhment hee had abidden for his iealouſie. The Monkes were proude of this miracle, and knewe that their Abbey ſhould bee more famous for this ſtrange wonder, and ſtraight ſent for his wife and his neighbours: who when they came, firſt the Abbot reuealed vnto them, howe that hee and his Monkes hearing the continuall plaintes and praiers the poore widow made for hir huſband; he did likewiſe with ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Oriſons intreat of God, that if it were his wil, he would ſhew a miracle in him, and reſtore him to life: and nowe my Maiſters and friendes quoth hee, ſée the difference betwéene the praiers of an Abbot, and the praiers of a lay man: for fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low me and you ſhall ſée what effect they haue taken. With that he carried them into the parlor where the Farmer was, aſſoone as they ſawe him, they were all amazed, and his wife fel down in a ſound: wherupon reuiuing hir he began to ſay, feare not wife, nor you gentle neighbours, &amp; doubt not of me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for I am by this holy man and my wiues praiers reſtor<add>ed to</add> life hauing béene in that moſt vile place of purgato<add>ry where</add> there is nothing but darkenes and Deuils: th<add>ere I have tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     </add>mented for all my ſinnes, but eſpecially for <add>my Jealousy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     </add>ing euery day puniſht till my wiues praie<add>rs deliverd me; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     </add>ny a fable beſide of his owne inuention d<add>eclared to them</add> he had ſéene in purgatory. At laſt as he v<add>owed to reform his</add> wife fell about his necke and kiſt him, <add>every one pleas'd &amp;</add> all the neighbours reioiced, and di<add>vers praiſd the Abot</add> for his holines. Vpon this he and <add>his wife reconciled, walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     </add>ed him home to his houſe ſolem<add>ly proclaming thanks &amp;</add> there left him. This newes <add>was cauſe of great</add> gaine by the Abbot of <hi>Wickam</hi> 
                     <add>who grew famous in that</add> country, that al men had him <add>in reverance as very</add>
                     <pb n="72" facs="tcp:10138:41" rendition="simple:additions"/> holy and vertuous, and diuers came to ſée the Farmer from farre: all which he did certifie what he had ſéen in purgatory, what great puniſhment for ſundry ſinnes but eſpecially for iealouſie. Thus he not onely exhorted all men from ſuſpition of their wiues, but euer after gaue his wife ſuch libertie, that ſhée might at hir owne pleaſure be familiar with the Abbot.</p>
                  <p>The Somner hauing told his tale, the people commended the great deuotion of the Abbot, wiſhing all iealous fooles to paſſe the like purgatory. The Cobler hee commended all, and ſaid, that they were now welcome to Graueſend: euery man to his purſe &amp; lookt in it for his two pence to pay his fare: and when they had done, they roſe and went into the towne to drinke: and becauſe they went moſt of them to <hi>Caunterburie,</hi> they went all to one Inne, where they beganne to deſcant and diſcourſe of the tales that had paſt: I can quoth the Cobler re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member them all, &amp; very néere verbatim collect &amp; gather them together: which by the grace of God gentlemen, I meane to doe, and then to ſet them out in a pamphlet vnder mine owne name, as an inuectiue againſt <hi>Tarltons newes out of Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie:</hi> and then if you pleaſe to ſend to the <hi>Printer,</hi> I wil leaue a token, that euery one of you that tolde a tale, ſhall haue a <add>Bok</add>e for his labour. In the meane time till I haue perfected <add>it I'll la</add>ye my Coblers ſtoole aſide, and my ſelfe become an <add>Author</add>. I hope you ſhall finde mee ſo fichent in mine En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <add>glish, if I</add> would ſtudy you would report I might for my <add>wit vie a</add> 
                     <hi>
                        <add>Lil</add>ly, Greene,</hi> or any other in excellency of <add>ſtile. T</add>hey all laught, paid their ſhot, and <add>went with</add>the merry Cobler towards <hi>Caunterburie.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>NIS.</hi>
            </trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:10138:41"/>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:10138:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:10138:42"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
